Welcome back to CS231n lecture 11.
CS231n 강의 11에 다시 오신 것을 환영합니다.
Today, we're going to talk about large-scale distributed
오늘은 대규모 분산 훈련에 대해 이야기할
training.
것입니다.
And this is a pretty exciting topic,
이 주제는 매우 흥미로운데,
because this is basically how all neural networks get
이는 기본적으로 현재 모든 신경망이 실제로
trained in practice today.
훈련되는 방식이기 때문입니다.
When you look at large models from startups, from industries,
스타트업, 산업, 심지어 학계에서 대규모
even in academia, really large-scale
모델을 보면, 현재 딥러닝에서는
is the new norm in deep learning nowadays.
정말 대규모가 새로운 표준입니다.
And that's actually something that's
사실, 이 수업을
changed quite a lot in the last 10 years
시작한 지난 10년 동안
since we started this class.
많이 변화한 부분입니다.
10 years ago, it was actually pretty
10년 전에는 모든 모델을 기본적으로 하나의
common to train all models basically
GPU, 하나의 장치에서
on one GPU, one device, and it was
훈련하는 것이 일반적이었고, 여러
fairly uncommon to train on multiple devices.
장치에서 훈련하는 것은 드물었습니다.
But as we'll see nowadays, the new norm
하지만 요즘은 모델을 수십,
is to train models on tens, hundreds, thousands, even
수백, 수천, 심지어 수만 개의 장치에서 동시에
tens of thousands of devices concurrently.
훈련하는 것이 새로운 표준입니다.
So we need to develop new algorithms
그래서 이를 위해
and new ways of thinking in order to do that.
새로운 알고리즘과 사고 방식을 개발해야 합니다.
And as a bit of running example through today's lecture,
오늘 강의의 예로 Llama3-405B에
we're going to be talking a lot about Llama3-405B,
대해 많이 이야기할 것입니다. 이
not because this is the best model or the most interesting
모델이 가장 좋은 모델이나 가장
model, but because this is a model that this is a fairly
흥미로운 모델이 아니라, 훈련
close to state-of-the-art model that actually shares a lot
방법, 모델 아키텍처 등 많은
of the implementation details of how it was trained,
구현 세부사항을 공유하는 최신
the model architecture, everything like that.
모델에 가깝기 때문입니다.
There's a lot of really amazing, powerful models
최근 몇 년 동안 Google,
that have been trained in the last couple of years,
OpenAI, Anthropic 등에서 훈련된
from Google, from OpenAI, from Anthropic, from others.
정말 놀랍고 강력한 모델들이 많이 있습니다.
But basically they don't share any details whatsoever
하지만 기본적으로 그들은 더 이상 모델에 대한
about their models anymore.
세부사항을 공유하지 않습니다.
There's a very famous quote that marked a sea change
2023년 GPT4 논문에서 산업의
in the industry to me that was in the GPT4 paper back in 2023.
큰 변화를 나타내는 매우 유명한 인용구가 있습니다.
So when they released the GPT4 model, they said,
GPT4 모델을 출시할 때, 그들은 "경쟁
"Given both the competitive landscape and the safety
환경과 GPT4와 같은 대규모 모델의
implications of large-scale models like GPT4, this report,
안전성 문제를 고려할 때, 이 보고서, 즉 그들이 작성한
meaning the paper they wrote about GPT4,
GPT4에 대한 논문은 모델 크기,
contains no further details about the architecture,
하드웨어, 훈련 컴퓨트, 데이터 세트 구성,
including model size, hardware, training compute,
훈련 방법 또는 유사한 것에 대한 추가
data set construction, training method, or similar."
세부정보를 포함하지 않습니다."라고 말했습니다.
And that's basically the news.
이게 기본적으로 뉴스입니다.
That's basically been the state-of-the-art for large-scale
지난 3년 동안 GPT4 이후
models the last three years since GPT4.
대규모 모델의 최신 상태였습니다.
They don't tell you anything about anything.
그들은 아무것도 알려주지 않습니다.
They'll tell you nothing about the model.
모델에 대해 아무것도 말하지 않을 것입니다.
You'll be lucky if they'll tell you it's a transformer.
그들이 트랜스포머라고 말해주면 행운입니다.
They might tell you that much.
그 정도는 말해줄지도 모릅니다.
So Llama3 is notable, not because it's
그래서 Llama3는 최고의 모델이
the best model out there, but because it's
아니라 가장 개방적인 모델 중
one of the most open models out there.
하나라는 점에서 주목할 만합니다.
So this is a large language model that was trained by Meta
이 모델은 Meta에 의해 훈련된 대형
and released open source about a year ago, in April 2024.
언어 모델로, 2024년 4월에 오픈 소스로 출시되었습니다.
And unlike OpenAI, the paper actually
OpenAI와 달리, 이 논문은
does share a lot of the details about the model training.
모델 훈련에 대한 많은 세부사항을 공유합니다.
Not too much about the data set, a lot
데이터 세트에 대한 정보는 많지
about the system infrastructure that was used to train it.
않지만, 훈련에 사용된 시스템 인프라에 대한 정보는 많습니다.
So this is something that we--
이것은 우리가-- 그리고
and this gives us a peek into how large-scale LLMs are
이것은 현재 대규모 LLM이 실제로 어떻게 훈련되는지를
actually trained these days.
엿볼 수 있게 해줍니다.
And by the way, there is a new Llama4 model
그런데, 지난달 2025년 4월에
that just came out from Meta last month, April 2025.
Meta에서 새로운 Llama4 모델이 출시되었습니다.
So there are slightly better models out there in open source
이미 오픈 소스에는 약간 더 나은 모델들이 있지만,
already, but there's no paper on Llama4 yet.
Llama4에 대한 논문은 아직 없습니다.
So I'm excited to read that one hopefully
그래서 몇 달 후에 나올 때 그
when it comes out in a couple of months
논문을 읽고 새로운
and see what can we learn from the new generation of Llama
Llama 훈련 세대에서 무엇을 배울 수 있을지 기대하고
training.
있습니다.
But just as a running example through today's lecture,
하지만 오늘 강의의 예로
we'll be pointing out a lot of examples
Llama3-405B
from the Llama3-405B model for this reason.
모델의 많은 예를 지적할 것입니다.
OK, so there's basically two things
좋습니다, 오늘 이야기하고
that I want to talk about today.
싶은 두 가지가 있습니다.
One is a bit about GPU hardware, and the other
하나는 GPU 하드웨어에 대한 것이고, 다른 하나는
is how to train on lots of GPUs.
많은 GPU에서 훈련하는 방법입니다.
So I want to give you a sense both of what
그래서 이들이 실행되는 하드웨어가
actually is the hardware that these things execute on,
실제로 무엇인지와 많은 GPU에서
as well as the algorithms that we need to use in order
훈련하기 위해 필요한 알고리즘에 대한
to train on a lot of them.
감각을 드리고 싶습니다.
So first, we're going to talk a little bit about GPU hardware.
먼저 GPU 하드웨어에 대해 조금 이야기하겠습니다.
So GPU, for those of you that don't know,
GPU는 잘 모르는 분들을 위해
is Graphics Processing Unit.
그래픽 처리 장치입니다.
These were specialized coprocessors
이것들은 원래 컴퓨터 그래픽을
that were originally developed for computer graphics.
위해 개발된 전문 코프로세서였습니다.
And they turned out to be very useful
그리고 이들은 매우 유용한 일반화 가능한
generalizable parallel processors.
병렬 프로세서로 판명되었습니다.
It's actually very fitting to be giving
이 강의를 이 방에서
this lecture in this room, because this
하는 것은 매우 적합합니다.
is the Huang auditorium.
이곳은 황 강당입니다.
Jen-Hsun Huang is the CEO and founder
Jen-Hsun Huang은
of NVIDIA, which is the biggest company right now
NVIDIA의 CEO이자 창립자로, 현재 가장
and has been for the last couple of decades in producing GPUs,
큰 GPU 제조 회사입니다. 게임과 ML
both for gaming and for ML.
모두를 위해 GPU를 생산해왔습니다.
So these things started off basically for graphics.
이것들은 기본적으로 그래픽을 위해 시작되었습니다.
Because if you think about it, when
컴퓨터 그래픽을 할 때
you're doing computer graphics, you
화면에 많은 픽셀을
need to generate a lot of pixels on the screen.
생성해야 하기 때문입니다.
You need to process lots of little pieces
그 픽셀을 생성하기 위해 많은 작은
of primitive geometry to produce those pixels.
기본 기하학 조각을 처리해야 합니다.
So it's very natural to do a lot of computation all in parallel
그래픽 작업을 할 때 많은 계산을 병렬로 수행하는
when you're doing computer graphics.
것이 매우 자연스럽습니다.
So people quickly figured out that this hardware that
사람들은 컴퓨터 그래픽을 위해 만들어진 이
had been built, intended to use in computer graphics
하드웨어가 훨씬 더 일반적인
could actually be used for much more
병렬 계산에도
general pieces of parallel computation as well.
사용될 수 있다는 것을 빠르게 알아냈습니다.
So in the early days in the early 2000s,
2000년대 초반에 연구자들은 이 그래픽 카드를
researchers figured out how they could contort these graphics
일반화 가능한 병렬 프로그래밍을
cards into doing generalizable parallel programming.
수행하도록 변형할 수 있는 방법을 알아냈습니다.
And then moving on towards the end of the 2000s
그리고 2000년대 후반과
and into the 2010s, NVIDIA really picked up this
2010년대 초반으로 넘어가면서 NVIDIA는
and developed these things, marketed them,
이를 발전시키고 마케팅하며
built them with the intention of being generalized parallel
일반화된 병렬 프로세서로 만들기 위해
processors.
노력했습니다.
They didn't quite know at the time what exactly they were
당시 그들이 정확히 무엇에 사용될지 알지는
going to be used for, I think.
못했던 것 같습니다.
I think they had this general idea that parallel processing
그들은 병렬 처리가 중요할 것이라는
was going to be important, and they really capitalized on deep
일반적인 생각을 가지고 있었고, 2010년대
learning when it started to take off in the early 2010s.
초반에 딥러닝이 시작될 때 이를 잘 활용했습니다.
Much to NVIDIA's credit, I think they really realized
NVIDIA의 공로 덕분에 그들은
the potential of this research area very early,
이 연구 분야의 잠재력을 매우 일찍,
even in the early 2010s and started putting a ton
2010년대 초반에 인식하고 그들의 하드웨어가
of resources into making sure that their hardware was really
딥러닝 훈련에 정말 유용하도록
useful for deep learning training.
많은 자원을 투입하기 시작했습니다.
And it's basically been the main way
그리고 이는 10년 넘게 사람들이
that people train large scale deep learning models
대규모 딥러닝 모델을 훈련하는 주요
for more than a decade now.
방법이 되어왔습니다.
That's starting to change, as we'll see a little bit,
조금씩 변화하고 있지만,
but their chips are the main one that people use.
그들의 칩은 사람들이 주로 사용하는 것입니다.
So I always like looking inside these things
그래서 저는 항상 이 것들을 들여다보고 그 안에 무엇이
and seeing what's in them.
있는지 보는 것을 좋아합니다.
So this is a picture of the NVIDIA H100,
이것은 현재 딥러닝
which is the mainstay of deep learning training
훈련의 주축인 NVIDIA H100의
right now, today.
사진입니다.
There's a next generation that just came out,
다음 세대가 방금 출시되었지만,
but it's not really accessible yet.
아직 접근할 수 없습니다.
I haven't trained anything on it yet.
저는 아직 그것으로 아무것도 훈련하지 않았습니다.
So this is the state-of-the-art right now.
그래서 이것이 현재의 최첨단입니다.
Inside this NVIDIA GPU, inside this H100 GPU in the middle
이 NVIDIA GPU, 즉 가운데 있는 H100 GPU 내부에는 이러한
here are these compute cores.
컴퓨트 코어가 있습니다.
And surrounding that are 80 gigabytes of HBM
그리고 그 주위에는 80기가바이트의 HBM 메모리,
memory, high-bandwidth memory.
고대역폭 메모리가 있습니다.
So you can see the memory is separated
메모리가 컴퓨트 코어와 분리되어 있는
from the compute cores.
것을 볼 수 있습니다.
They need to move.
그들은 이동해야 합니다.
They need to talk to each other over this bus
그들은 GPU 메모리와 코어 간에 데이터를
to move data back and forth from the GPU memory into the cores.
주고받기 위해 이 버스를 통해 서로 통신해야 합니다.
And it can do that at a speed of about 3 terabytes per second,
그리고 이는 초당 약 3테라바이트의 속도로 데이터를 이동할 수
which is a lot of bits moving around.
있습니다. 이는 많은 비트가 이동하는 것입니다.
Now, if we dive deeper inside the GPU cores,
이제 GPU 코어 내부를 더 깊이 들여다보면, 그
we see that in the middle in that compute core part,
컴퓨트 코어 부분의 중앙에 약
we've got a smaller piece of memory,
50메가바이트의 L2 캐시라는
about 50 megabytes of L2 cache that
훨씬 더 작은 메모리가 있습니다.
is much, much smaller than the 80 gigabytes of HBM memory.
이는 80기가바이트의 HBM 메모리보다 훨씬 작습니다.
But it's very, very close to the actual computing elements.
하지만 이는 실제 컴퓨팅 요소와 매우 가까이 있습니다.
So they can be accessed much more quickly
그래서 컴퓨트 코어에서 훨씬 더
from the compute cores.
빠르게 접근할 수 있습니다.
And then the real heart of the thing
그리고 이 장치의 진정한
are these 132 Streaming Multiprocessors or SMs.
핵심은 132개의 스트리밍 멀티프로세서(SM)입니다.
These are independent parallel cores.
이들은 독립적인 병렬 코어입니다.
They're a little bit more powerful
일반 CPU 코어보다 몇 가지
in some ways than a typical CPU core,
면에서 더 강력합니다. 왜냐하면 더 많은
because they can do a lot more parallelism.
병렬 처리를 할 수 있기 때문입니다.
But they're a lot weaker than a typical CPU
하지만 일반 CPU 코어에 비해 여러
core also in a lot of ways, because they tend
면에서 훨씬 약합니다. 왜냐하면 클럭
to have slower clock speeds.
속도가 느리기 때문입니다.
They can't do as much instruction prediction,
명령어 예측이나 분기 예측을
as much branch prediction.
많이 할 수 없습니다.
So it's really hard to make exact apples
그래서 이러한 GPU 코어와
to apples comparisons between these GPU cores and the CPU
CPU 코어 간의 정확한 비교는 정말
cores.
어렵습니다.
But I usually think of these streaming multiprocessors
하지만 저는 이러한 스트리밍 멀티프로세서를
as roughly akin to a CPU core.
대략 CPU 코어와 유사하다고 생각합니다.
Also, I know someone's going to go back home and actually
또한 누군가는 집에 가서 이 화면의 작은
count all the little boxes on this screen,
박스들을 모두 세어볼 것이고, 실제로
and you'll see that there are actually 144 of them
144개가 있다는 것을 알게 될 것입니다. 제가
and when I've said there's only 132.
132개라고 말했을 때 말이죠.
Why is that?
왜 그럴까요?
It's because all GPU hardware uses a process called binning,
모든 GPU 하드웨어는 빈닝이라는 과정을 사용합니다. 이
where making these things, they have so many transistors, so
과정에서 이들을 만들 때, 많은 트랜지스터와 작은
many little computing elements.
컴퓨팅 요소가 있습니다.
No matter how much money they pour into the process,
얼마나 많은 돈을 쏟아 부어도
they just don't come out perfectly.
완벽하게 나오지 않습니다.
Some of them always end up a little bit messed up.
항상 약간 망가진 것들이 생깁니다.
So they plan for that in the development of their products.
그래서 그들은 제품 개발에서 이를 계획합니다.
And they say, we're going to try to make a chip.
그리고 그들은 칩을 만들려고 합니다.
The full chip in theory has 144, but none of the chips
이론적으로 전체 칩은 144개를 가지고 있지만, 완벽한
are perfect.
칩은 없습니다.
But we know we'll get a reasonable number of those
하지만 최소한 132개가 작동하는
that have at least 132 that are functioning.
합리적인 수를 얻을 것이라는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So they tend to use this process of binning.
그래서 그들은 빈닝 과정을 사용합니다.
So then they actually only can sell
그럼 그들은 실제로 생산하려고
a much more larger proportion of the chips
했던 칩의
they tried to produce by only promising that 132 of them
훨씬 더 큰 비율을 판매할 수 있습니다. 단지 132개가
will be turned on.
켜질 것이라고 약속함으로써요.
Then we can dive even deeper inside one of those streaming
그런 다음 우리는 이러한 스트리밍 멀티프로세서 중 하나의 내부를 더
multiprocessors.
깊이 파고들 수 있습니다.
And then we can see even more what's
그리고 우리는 이러한 GPU 내부에서 무슨 일이 일어나고
going on inside of these GPUs.
있는지 더 많이 볼 수 있습니다.
So this is just one of the 132 active streaming
이것은 H100 내부의 132개 활성 스트리밍
multiprocessors inside an H100.
멀티프로세서 중 하나입니다.
And there's a couple interesting elements in here to look at.
여기에서 살펴볼 몇 가지 흥미로운 요소가 있습니다.
First, we see we have 256 kilobytes of L1 cache
먼저, 우리는 256킬로바이트의 L1 캐시와 레지스터
and register files.
파일이 있음을 봅니다.
So this continues the trend of the memory hierarchy in the GPU.
그래서 이것은 GPU의 메모리 계층 구조의 경향을 계속 이어갑니다.
We saw that in general, you thought you
우리는 일반적으로 깊은 학습을 배우고
were learning deep learning?
있다고 생각했습니까?
You're actually learning computer architecture.
사실 당신은 컴퓨터 아키텍처를 배우고 있습니다.
Sorry, it's a surprise.
죄송합니다, 놀라운 사실입니다.
And it turns out that memory hierarchy
그리고 메모리 계층 구조는 깊은
is really important for deep learning
학습과 모든 종류의 고성능
and for all kind of high performance computing.
컴퓨팅에 정말 중요하다는 것이 밝혀졌습니다.
And the general trend is that you
일반적인 경향은 계산
have larger bits of memory that are farther
코어에서 멀리 떨어진 더 큰 메모리
away from the compute cores.
조각을 갖는 것입니다.
And the closer you get to the compute cores,
계산 코어에 가까워질수록 더
you have smaller bits of memory but are much, much faster.
작은 메모리 조각이 있지만 훨씬 더 빠릅니다.
And it's really important to write--
이것은 정말 중요합니다--
well, if you're writing the low-level algorithms that
잘, 이러한 것들에서 실행되는 저수준
run on these things, it's very important
알고리즘을 작성하는 경우, 이
to be aware of this memory hierarchy
메모리 계층 구조를 인식하고
and to be very diligent in passing
서로 다른 메모리 계층
data between different phases of this memory hierarchy.
간에 데이터를 전달하는 데 매우 부지런해야 합니다.
And if you're writing performance GPU kernels,
그리고 성능 GPU 커널을 작성하는
you spend a lot of time trying to optimize that.
경우, 이를 최적화하는 데 많은 시간을 보냅니다.
So just to give you a flavor of that,
그래서 그에 대한 맛을 제공하기 위해,
we see the three levels of memory hierarchy in the H100.
우리는 H100의 메모리 계층 구조의 세 가지 수준을 봅니다.
You've got 256 kilobytes of L1 cache, 50 megabytes of L2 cache,
L1 캐시가 256킬로바이트, L2 캐시가 50메가바이트, 그리고 HBM
and then 80 gigabytes of HBM memory.
메모리가 80기가바이트 있습니다.
So those are the three primary levels
이것이 H100의 메모리
of memory hierarchy in the H100.
계층 구조의 세 가지 주요 수준입니다.
Then we've also got 128 of these FP32 cores.
그리고 우리는 이 FP32 코어가 128개 있습니다.
These are little arithmetic units
이들은 일반화된 부동 소수점
that can do generalized floating point operations.
연산을 수행할 수 있는 작은 산술 유닛입니다.
And in particular, each one of these 128 FP32 cores
특히 이 128개의 FP32 코어 각각은 a, x, b가
can compute ax plus b, where a, x, and b are all scalars.
모두 스칼라인 경우 ax + b를 계산할 수 있습니다.
It can perform that bit of computation in one clock cycle.
이 계산은 한 클럭 사이클 내에 수행할 수 있습니다.
So then if you add this all up, that ax plus b
따라서 이 모든 것을 합치면 ax + b는
is basically 1 multiply 1 addition,
기본적으로 1 곱하기 1
and you've got 128 of these cores.
더하기이며, 이 코어가 128개 있습니다.
This whole SM can do 256 floating point operations per SM
이 전체 SM은 장치의 클럭 사이클당 SM당 256개의 부동
per clock cycle of the device.
소수점 연산을 수행할 수 있습니다.
Then we'll also see that in red, we've
그리고 빨간색으로 표시된 부분에서,
got-- this is where the real magic happens, that in addition
여기서 진정한 마법이 일어납니다. 이
to these FP32 cores, there are also these four tensor cores.
FP32 코어 외에도 이 네 개의 텐서 코어가 있습니다.
I think the name is a little bit of a misnomer.
이름이 약간 오해의 소지가 있다고 생각합니다.
These are actually matrix cores.
이들은 실제로 행렬 코어입니다.
What each of these little tensor cores does
각 텐서 코어는
is they're special circuits that are designed.
특별히 설계된 회로입니다.
They only do one thing.
그들은 단 하나의 작업만 수행합니다.
They do matrix multiply.
행렬 곱셈을 수행합니다.
So each one of these little tensor cores
각 텐서 코어는 행렬 곱셈의
can do a single chunk of matrix multiply.
단일 청크를 수행할 수 있습니다.
In particular, I believe the H100 ones can do a 16--
특히 H100의 경우 입력 행렬 A는
input matrix A is 16 by 4, input matrix B is 4 by 8,
16x4, 입력 행렬 B는 4x8,
and then plus a bias matrix of a size 16 by 8.
그리고 편향 행렬은 16x8 크기입니다.
So it basically does ax plus b, where
즉, ax + b를 수행하는데, 여기서 a,
a, x, and b are little matrix chunks of this fixed size.
x, b는 고정 크기의 작은 행렬 청크입니다.
And it can do that one little chunk of matrix
각 텐서 코어는 클럭 사이클당 한
multiply once per tensor core per clock cycle.
번의 행렬 곱셈 청크를 수행할 수 있습니다.
So then if you multiply all these numbers out,
따라서 이 모든 숫자를 곱하면, 해당
you see that little matrix multiply of ax plus b of that
크기의 ax + b의 작은 행렬 곱셈은 1,024개의
particular size is 1,024 floating point operations,
부동 소수점 연산이 되며, 여기서 각 곱셈과 각
where that's counting each multiply,
덧셈이 하나의 부동
each add as a single floating point operation.
소수점 연산으로 계산됩니다.
We multiply that by the 4 tensor cores in the SM.
이것을 SM의 4개의 텐서 코어로 곱합니다.
And we see that the entire SM, if it's going through the tensor
그리고 텐서 코어를 통해 전체 SM은 클럭
cores, can do 4,096 floating point operations per SM per
사이클당 SM당 4,096개의 부동 소수점 연산을 수행할
clock cycle.
수 있습니다.
And this we need to compare with the 256
그리고 이것은 FP32 코어에서 얻을
that we can get from the FP32 cores.
수 있는 256과 비교해야 합니다.
And here we see that just like the tensor
여기서 텐서 코어가 모든 마법이 일어나는
cores are where all the magic happens.
곳이라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
This is where the main throughput of the device
이곳이 장치의 주요 처리량이 나오는
comes from.
곳입니다.
And if you're writing code that wants to run on these GPUs
이 GPU에서 실행되기를
and they can make maximum usage of them,
원하는 코드를 작성하는 경우,
you need to make maximum usage of these tensor cores.
최대한 텐서 코어를 활용해야 합니다.
Another interesting thing about these tensor cores
이 텐서 코어에 대한 또 다른 흥미로운 점은
is that they actually operate in mixed precision.
실제로 혼합 정밀도로 작동한다는 것입니다.
Rather than traditional floating point numbers,
전통적인 부동 소수점
which are normally 32-bit, the tensor cores tend to use a mixed
숫자(일반적으로 32비트) 대신, 텐서 코어는 보통
precision procedure, where the inputs are usually 16-bit.
16비트의 혼합 정밀도 절차를 사용합니다.
And there's a couple of different interesting 16-bit
오늘은 다룰 수 없는 몇
formats that they can use that we can't get into today.
가지 흥미로운 16비트 형식이 있습니다.
And they'll do the multiplications in this lower
곱셈은 이 낮은 정밀도 16비트에서
precision 16-bit and then do the additions,
수행하고, 덧셈과 누적은 더 높은
the accumulations in a higher precision 32-bit.
정밀도 32비트에서 수행합니다.
So these tensor cores take a low precision, 16-bit input,
따라서 이 텐서 코어는 낮은 정밀도 16비트 입력을 받아
and then do some of the intermediate computation
중간 계산을 수행하고, 더
and produce the outputs in a higher precision 32-bit.
높은 정밀도 32비트로 출력을 생성합니다.
And this is important because at the PyTorch layer,
이는 PyTorch 레이어에서 모델을 16비트로
if you forget to cast your model into 16-bit,
변환하는 것을 잊으면 부동 소수점 코어에서
it will run on the floating point cores.
실행되기 때문에 중요합니다.
Instead it will be 20 times slower than you expect.
대신 예상보다 20배 느리게 실행됩니다.
So this seems like a little bit of minutia,
이것은 사소한 것처럼 보이지만,
but it becomes very tangible when you mess up those data
PyTorch 코드에서 데이터 유형을
types in your PyTorch code.
잘못 다루면 매우 실질적으로 느껴집니다.
And then note, so GPUs are really fast,
그리고 GPU는 정말 빠르며,
and it's really crazy just how much faster they've
지난 10년 또는 15년 동안
gotten over the past decade or 15 years or so.
얼마나 더 빨라졌는지 정말 놀랍습니다.
So when I first started my PhD and was working on deep
제가 박사 과정을 처음 시작했을
learning, the state-of-the-art GPU that we were all using was
때 사용하던 최첨단 GPU는
this K40 GPU, which was released back in 2013.
2013년에 출시된 K40 GPU였습니다.
And this thing could do just a 5 teraflops of FP32 compute
이 장치는 전체 장치에서 5 테라플롭스의 FP32 연산을 수행할
for the whole device.
수 있었습니다.
All right, so I should explain the graph.
그래프를 설명해야 합니다.
So the x-axis is time ranging from about 2013
x축은 2013년부터 현재까지의 시간을
up to present day.
나타냅니다.
And then the y-axis is the peak throughput
y축은 각 장치의
of each of these devices measured in terms of teraflops
초당 테라플롭스 기준으로 측정된 최대
per second per device.
처리량입니다.
And you can see the graph goes up a lot.
그래프가 많이 상승하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
But there's something salient to notice here
하지만 K40에서 P100으로
is that from the K40 to the P100,
넘어가면서 V100에서 정말 놀라운
something really amazing happened in the V100,
일이 발생했습니다. V100은
which came out towards the end of my PhD and around 2016, 2017,
제 박사 과정이 끝날 무렵인 2016년, 2017년에
and that the V100 was the first device that
출시되었고, 텐서 코어를 처음
introduced these tensor cores.
도입한 장치였습니다.
And since then, more recent devices
그 이후로 더 최근의 장치들은 더 많은 텐서 코어,
have gotten more tensor cores, bigger tensor cores,
더 큰 텐서 코어, 텐서 코어에
more of the device area allocated to tensor cores,
할당된 장치 면적이 늘어나면서
and this has resulted in a gigantic increase
지난 10년 또는 15년 동안
in the throughput of these devices over the past 10
이러한 장치의 처리량이 엄청나게
or 15 years.
증가했습니다.
And the most recent device is this B200
가장 최근의 장치는 공식 발표된
that was formally announced.
B200입니다.
It's slowly rolling out now.
현재 천천히 출시되고 있습니다.
This one in theory has about 83.3 teraflops per second
이론적으로 이 장치는 FP32 연산에서 초당 약 83.3 테라플롭스, 텐서 코어에서 혼합
of FP32 compute and 5,000 teraflops per second in theory
정밀도 연산으로 초당 5,000
of mixed precision compute on the tensor cores.
테라플롭스를 가지고 있습니다.
So if you step back, this is like literally we've been living
한 걸음 물러서서 보면, 우리는 지난
through a 1,000 fold increase in computation over the past 12
12년 동안 실제로 1,000배의 연산 증가를 경험하고
years.
있습니다.
And that's just that the per device level.
이는 장치 수준에서의 이야기입니다.
So one explanation of why AI has gotten so good in the last 10
지난 10년 동안 AI가 이렇게 좋아진
years, what has happened?
이유는 무엇일까요?
This is the answer.
이것이 그 답입니다.
There's now a source of computation that we're taking
이제 우리가 활용하고 있는 연산의 원천이
advantage of, and it's gone up by 1,000x in the last decade.
있으며, 지난 10년 동안 1,000배 증가했습니다.
Anytime anything in the world changes by 1,000x,
세상의 어떤 것이 1,000배 변화하면,
you should step up and pay attention because that's going
주목해야 합니다. 이는 우리의
to cause major changes in our technological capabilities.
기술적 능력에 큰 변화를 가져올 것입니다.
And this 1,000x improvement, I think,
이 1,000배 개선이 지난
is the major driver of improvement in deep learning
10년 동안 딥러닝 개선의 주요
over the past decade.
원동력이라고 생각합니다.
So it does not have 5,000 tensor cores.
따라서 5,000개의 텐서 코어가 있는 것은 아닙니다.
That's 5,000 teraflops of compute on the tensor cores.
텐서 코어에서의 연산이 5,000 테라플롭스입니다.
Yeah.
네.
So we always try to distinguish between the compute
우리는 항상 텐서 코어에서의
on the tensor cores versus the compute on the FP32 cores.
연산과 FP32 코어에서의 연산을 구분하려고 합니다.
So this is already crazy.
이것은 이미 미쳤습니다.
It's already crazy that there's been a 1,000 increase
손에 쥘 수 있는 장치에서 1,000배
in a device that you can hold in your hands.
증가한 것은 이미 미친 일입니다.
I've held a K40 in my hands, and I've not had the opportunity
저는 K40을 손에 쥐어본 적이 있고, B100을 쥐어볼
to hold a B100.
기회는 없었습니다.
But they feel like the same physical object.
하지만 두 장치는 같은 물리적 객체처럼 느껴집니다.
It's like about the same size, about the same weight,
크기와 무게가 비슷하고, 생김새도 비슷하지만,
looks the same, but the one from today is 1,000 times faster than
오늘날의 장치는 12년 전의 장치보다 1,
the one from 12 years ago.
000배 빠릅니다.
That's insane.
정말 미친 일입니다.
But it gets even crazier because we don't train on one GPU.
하지만 더 미친 것은 우리가 하나의 GPU에서 훈련하지 않는다는 것입니다.
I said that when the K40 first came out in 2013,
K40이 2013년에 처음 출시되었을 때, 실제로 많은
it actually was common to train a lot of models on just one GPU.
모델을 하나의 GPU에서 훈련하는 것이 일반적이었습니다.
But today, we're training not just on one GPU.
하지만 오늘 우리는 하나의 GPU에서만 훈련하지 않습니다.
We're training on thousands, tens of thousands,
우리는 수천, 수만, 때로는 수십만
sometimes hundreds of thousands of GPUs,
개의 GPU에서 훈련하고 있으며, 이
all working together to train one model.
모든 GPU가 함께 작업하여 하나의 모델을 훈련합니다.
So stack that on top of this 1,000 fold increase in per
그래서 이것을 장치당 처리량이 1,000배 증가한 것
device throughput.
위에 쌓아보세요.
And something truly insane has happened in the past decade.
그리고 지난 10년 동안 정말 미친 일이 일어났습니다.
So we've looked inside the GPU.
그래서 우리는 GPU 내부를 살펴보았습니다.
Now from here, I want to zoom out and put that GPU in context,
이제 여기서 저는 GPU를 개별 장치가
not looking at individual devices,
아닌, 우리가 구축하는
but thinking about the modern GPU clusters
현대 GPU 클러스터의
that we build that stitch a lot of these things together.
맥락에서 확대하고 싶습니다.
So we've already seen a single H100 GPU.
우리는 이미 단일 H100 GPU를 보았습니다.
And here we can think of it as another level
여기서 우리는 그것을 또 다른 메모리 계층의
of memory hierarchy.
수준으로 생각할 수 있습니다.
We already saw inside the H100, there
우리는 H100 내부를 살펴보았고,
were three layers of memory hierarchy
계산 요소에 가까워질수록 세
as we got closer to the compute elements.
개의 메모리 계층이 있었습니다.
And as you got farther away from the compute elements,
계산 요소에서 멀어질수록 대역폭,
the bandwidth, the memory bandwidth,
메모리 대역폭, 시스템의
the ability of the device to move bits around
다양한 부분 간에 비트를 이동할
between different parts of the system gets slower.
수 있는 장치의 능력이 느려집니다.
And this trend actually continues
이 경향은 단일 장치의
once you escape the bounds of a single device
경계를 벗어나 전체 데이터
and imagine these in the context of a full data center.
센터의 맥락에서 상상할 때 계속됩니다.
So here we saw a single H100 GPU gets about 3 terabytes
여기서 우리는 단일 H100 GPU가 약 3테라바이트의 메모리 대역폭을
of memory bandwidth.
가진다는 것을 보았습니다.
That's the GPU memory talking from its own HBM memory
이는 GPU 메모리가 자신의 HBM 메모리에서 자신의 계산 요소로
to its own compute elements, 3 terabytes per second.
3테라바이트 per 초로 이야기하는 것입니다.
It can move bits around.
비트를 이동할 수 있습니다.
But these things typically live inside a GPU server.
하지만 이러한 것들은 일반적으로 GPU 서버 내부에 있습니다.
Almost all GPU servers have eight devices in one big box,
거의 모든 GPU 서버는 하나의 큰 박스에 8개의 장치를 가지고 있으며,
and those GPUs can talk to each other.
이러한 GPU는 서로 통신할 수 있습니다.
And they typically talk to each other
서버 내의 어떤 GPU에서
at a rate of about 900 gigabytes per second
다른 GPU로 약 900기가바이트
from any one GPU in the server to any other GPU in the server.
per 초의 속도로 서로 통신하는 것이 일반적입니다.
So you can see that's like a 3x less memory communication
그래서 이는 하나의 장치 내부에서 GPU가 이야기하는
bandwidth compared to the GPU talking inside one device.
것에 비해 메모리 통신 대역폭이 3배 낮다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
And here we again turn to Llama3.
그리고 여기서 우리는 다시 Llama3로 돌아갑니다.
A lot of major players don't publish
많은 주요 업체들이 훈련 클러스터에 대한 많은
a lot of details on their training clusters,
세부 정보를 공개하지 않지만, Llama3
but the Llama3 technical report did actually
기술 보고서는 실제로 그들의 훈련
give a lot of details around their training clusters.
클러스터에 대한 많은 세부 정보를 제공했습니다.
So from here, some of the specifics
그래서 여기서 일부 세부
probably vary a little bit from cluster to cluster.
사항은 클러스터마다 약간 다를 수 있습니다.
But these are now numbers from the Llama3 cluster that
하지만 이제 이것은 그들의 모델을
was used to train their models.
훈련하는 데 사용된 Llama3 클러스터의 숫자입니다.
So they give in one GPU box.
그들은 하나의 GPU 박스에서 제공합니다.
They stack two of those box into one server rack.
그들은 하나의 서버 랙에 두 개의 박스를 쌓습니다.
And a server rack, if you haven't seen it,
서버 랙은 보지
they're about 6 feet tall, like about the size of a person,
못했다면 약 6피트 높이로,
to just get a mental picture of one of those things.
사람 크기 정도입니다.
So one server rack has two servers inside
하나의 서버 랙에는 두 개의 서버가
of it, a total of 16 GPUs.
들어 있으며, 총 16개의 GPU가 있습니다.
Then we connect a lot of server racks together into a GPU pod.
그런 다음 우리는 많은 서버 랙을 연결하여 GPU 포드를 만듭니다.
The Llama3 cluster has GPU pods that are composed of 192 racks,
Llama3 클러스터는 192개의 랙으로 구성된 GPU 포드를 가지고
which is a total of 3,072 GPUs.
있으며, 총 3,072개의 GPU가 있습니다.
And these things have really high bandwidth connectors
이러한 것들은 모든 랙 간에 매우 높은
between all the different racks.
대역폭 커넥터를 가지고 있습니다.
And as a result, any pair of GPUs inside that pod
그 결과, 해당 포드 내의 GPU 쌍은 약 50기가바이트
can talk to each other at a rate of about 50 gigabytes
per 초의 속도로 서로 통신할 수
per second.
있습니다.
And now, you see, this is another 20x decrease in memory
이제 보시다시피, 이는 개별 서버가 이야기할 수
traffic between what an individual server can talk
있는 것과 전체 랙의 GPU가 서로 이야기할 수
and then what any GPU across an entire rack can talk to each
있는 것 간의 메모리 트래픽에서 또 다른 20배
other.
감소입니다.
So 3,072 GPUs seems like a lot of compute,
그래서 3,072개의 GPU는 많은 계산처럼
but it's nowhere near enough.
보이지만, 결코 충분하지 않습니다.
So we're going to stack those GPU pods together
그래서 우리는 그 GPU 포드를 함께 쌓아서
into a full GPU cluster.
전체 GPU 클러스터를 만들 것입니다.
So this is actually the full GPU cluster
그래서 이것은 Meta가 Llama3
that Meta built to train their Llama3 models.
모델을 훈련하기 위해 만든 전체 GPU 클러스터입니다.
This thing combines eight GPU pods together for a total
이것은 총 24,576개의 GPU를 위해
of 24,576 GPUs.
8개의 GPU 포드를 결합한 것입니다.
I could not find exact numbers on the memory traffic
이들 간의 메모리 트래픽에 대한 정확한 숫자는
between these things, but it's definitely
찾을 수 없었지만, 확실히
less than 50 gigabytes per second.
초당 50기가바이트보다 적습니다.
And by the way, this is not the largest GPU cluster in the world
그리고 이건 세계에서 가장 큰 GPU
by a long shot.
클러스터는 아닙니다.
It's the biggest one that I could quickly
제가 빠르게 정확한 숫자를 찾을 수 있는
find precise numbers on.
가장 큰 클러스터입니다.
But there are definitely GPU clusters out there in the world
하지만 세계에는 50,000개, 100,
that are 50,000 GPUs, 100,000 GPUs.
000개의 GPU 클러스터가 분명히 존재합니다.
They exist, and people train models on them.
그들은 존재하며, 사람들은 그 위에서 모델을 훈련합니다.
And the way that this works is it sort of scales out naturally.
이것이 작동하는 방식은 자연스럽게 확장됩니다.
So you would just cluster together more pods together
그래서 더 큰 클러스터를 만들기 위해
to create a bigger cluster, or you
더 많은 포드를 함께 클러스터링하거나,
might have another level of hierarchy
다른 슈퍼 포드와
where you might have a super pod that
연결되는 슈퍼 포드를
connects to other super pods to get you another level up.
가질 수 있는 또 다른 계층이 있을 수 있습니다.
How long do they train with that GPU cluster?
그 GPU 클러스터로 얼마나 훈련하나요?
I don't remember offhand for the Llama3 models,
Llama3 모델에 대해서는 정확히 기억나지
but there's been kind of a rule of thumb
않지만, 지난 10년
for the past decade is that the longest models that people train
동안의 경험칙은 사람들이 훈련하는 가장 긴
are usually on the order of months.
모델은 보통 몇 달 정도입니다.
And that I think has less to do with technology
그리고 이는 기술보다는 사람과 더 관련이
and more to do with people.
있다고 생각합니다.
When it comes to having progress, making plans, having
진전을 이루고, 계획을 세우고, 사람들이 작업하는
people work on things, it's very difficult
것과 관련해서는 매우 긴 훈련을
to have training runs that are very, very long.
갖는 것이 매우 어렵습니다.
So the longest training runs, the biggest state-of-the-art
그래서 가장 긴 훈련, 가장 최신의 모델은
models, I think are typically measured in months.
보통 몇 달로 측정된다고 생각합니다.
I would not be surprised if the very, very largest models,
GPT-4.5나 GPT-5와 같은
the GPT-4.5, the GPT-5, if those are pushing closer to a year
가장 큰 모델이 현재 1년에 가까워지고 있다면 놀라지
at this point.
않을 것입니다.
But it's pretty common to see training runs that
하지만 이러한 정말 큰 훈련
are on the order of a couple of months on these really
클러스터에서 몇 달 정도의 훈련을
big training clusters.
보는 것은 꽤 일반적입니다.
The question is, why do you organize servers into a rack
질문은, 왜 서버를 포드가 아니라
rather than in a pod?
랙에 조직하나요?
You got to put them somewhere.
어딘가에 두어야 합니다.
There's physical constraints on these things.
이런 것들에는 물리적 제약이 있습니다.
So server racks have been a standard unit
그래서 서버 랙은 수십 년 동안 데이터
in just data centers for decades at this point.
센터의 표준 단위였습니다.
So when these new devices came onto the scene of GPUs,
이 새로운 GPU 장치가 등장했을 때, 이는 다른
that gives you a different kind of server.
종류의 서버를 제공합니다.
They're a lot physically bigger.
물리적으로 훨씬 더 큽니다.
They have a lot more power, but you
전력이 훨씬 더 많지만,
can't redesign the whole data center from scratch overnight.
데이터 센터를 하룻밤 사이에 완전히 재설계할 수는 없습니다.
So as a result, the server rack has been a standard unit
결과적으로, 서버 랙은 표준 하드웨어 크기와
with standard hardware sizes and everything
함께 데이터 센터가 일반적으로
that the data centers are typically built around.
구축되는 표준 단위가 되었습니다.
How much physical space does like a cluster or something
클러스터나 무언가가 얼마나 많은 물리적 공간을
[INAUDIBLE]?
차지하나요?
Oh, that's a great question.
아, 그건 좋은 질문입니다.
So you should think of a single server
단일 서버 랙은 대략
rack as being like around 6, 8 feet tall, something like that,
6~8피트 정도의 높이로 생각해야
like, about this big.
합니다.
So maybe a server rack would be around the size of this podium
그래서 아마도 서버 랙은 이 강단의 크기
and about as tall as me.
정도이고 제 키 정도의 높이일 것입니다.
Then you've got 192 racks in a pod.
그런 다음 포드에는 192개의 랙이 있습니다.
So imagine 200 of these podiums.
그래서 이 강단 200개를 상상해 보세요.
How big would that be?
그것은 얼마나 클까요?
And then multiply that by 8.
그것을 8로 곱하세요.
But that's actually a little bit of an underestimate,
하지만 실제로는 약간 과소 추정입니다. 왜냐하면
because you typically organize these things in rows
일반적으로 사람들이 그 사이를 걸을 수 있도록
so people can actually walk between them.
이러한 것들을 행으로 정리하기 때문입니다.
And there's more hardware that you
클러스터에 패킹해야 할
need to pack into the cluster, not just the compute racks.
하드웨어가 더 있습니다. 단순히 컴퓨트 랙만이 아닙니다.
So in addition to the compute racks that have the physical GPU
물리적 GPU 서버가 있는 컴퓨트 랙 외에도
servers, there will be other racks that
네트워킹 하드웨어를 포함하는
contain networking hardware.
다른 랙이 있을 것입니다.
We've got a lot of bits that need to fly around
모든 장치 간에 이동해야 할 비트가
between all these devices.
많습니다.
So they'll be dedicated racks that
그래서 네트워킹 하드웨어만을 보관하는
only hold networking hardware.
전용 랙이 있을 것입니다.
There will also be dedicated racks
저장 하드웨어만을 보관하는
that only hold storage hardware, because you
전용 랙도 있을 것입니다. 훈련
need to store that training data somewhere and get that
데이터를 어딘가에 저장하고 장치로
into your devices.
가져와야 하니까요.
So these things can take up quite a lot of space.
이러한 것들은 꽤 많은 공간을 차지할 수 있습니다.
Oh yeah.
아, 맞아요.
Question is, when you go to these big clusters,
질문은, 이러한 큰 클러스터에 가면 작은
do the smaller units of compute maintain the higher throughput?
컴퓨트 유닛들이 더 높은 처리량을 유지하나요?
And yes, they do.
네, 유지합니다.
And that's part of the secret and the challenge of designing
이 시스템을 설계하는 비밀과 도전의
for these systems, because you ideally
일부입니다. 가능할 때
want to take advantage of the fast communication
빠른 통신을 활용하고,
when you can get it, but also fall back
규모를 키울 때 더 큰
gracefully to the slower communication on the larger
유닛에서 느린 통신으로
units as you scale up.
우아하게 되돌아가고 싶기 때문입니다.
Oh, how hot does it get?
오, 얼마나 뜨거워지나요?
Pretty hot.
꽤 뜨겁습니다.
If any of you is a gamer and has a 4090 GPU or 5080
여기 계신 분 중에 게이머가 있고 집에 4090
GPU in your desktop at home, a single 4090 GPU,
GPU나 5080 GPU가 있다면, 단일 4090 GPU가 게임을
if you're playing games, will heat up your room,
할 때 방을 데우고 창문을
make you want to open the window.
열고 싶게 만들 것입니다.
It will make the room physically warmer.
방을 물리적으로 더 따뜻하게 만들 것입니다.
So imagine if that's what a single gaming
하나의 게임 GPU가 평균 크기의
GPU can do to an average-sized room,
방에 미치는 영향을 상상해
yeah, there's some serious cooling requirements
보세요. 네, 데이터 센터에
for these things once you stack tens of thousands of them
수만 개를 쌓으면 심각한 냉각 요구
in a big data center.
사항이 있습니다.
Although another interesting thing is about--
또 다른 흥미로운 점은 냉각이 미친
I mean, the cooling gets crazy.
듯이 변한다는 것입니다.
So a gaming desktop will typically
게임용 데스크탑은 일반적으로
be air cooled, sometimes water cooled.
공랭식이고, 때때로 수랭식입니다.
And then you can design different cooling systems.
그리고 다양한 냉각 시스템을 설계할 수 있습니다.
And you can go nuts on the hardware
여기에서 모든 것을
here to try to optimize all this stuff.
최적화하기 위해 하드웨어에 미쳐도 됩니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
So I think this stuff is super cool.
이것들은 정말 멋진 것이라고 생각합니다.
It's just imagining like these GPUs are not just
이 GPU들이 단순히 구름 속에 떠다니는 신화적인
mythical creatures that are floating around in the cloud.
존재가 아니라는 것을 상상하는 것입니다.
These are actual physical atoms that someone built and stacked
이들은 누군가가 만들고 방 어딘가에 쌓아놓은 실제
up in a room somewhere.
물리적 원자입니다.
And it's really interesting to imagine what they look like.
그들이 어떻게 생겼는지 상상하는 것이 정말 흥미롭습니다.
And so basically one kind of mindset shift
그래서 기본적으로 이러한 큰 GPU 클러스터로 이동할
when we moved to these big GPU clusters
때의 사고 방식 변화는
is actually thinking not so much about the individual devices,
개별 장치나 개별 서버에 대해 생각하는
about the individual servers.
것이 아닙니다.
I basically tried to think of the entire data
저는 전체 데이터 센터를 하나의
center as one big computer.
큰 컴퓨터로 생각하려고 했습니다.
And this big computer in this case has 24,000 GPUs,
이 큰 컴퓨터는 24,000개의 GPU, GPU에 1.
1.8 terabytes of HBM memory on the GPUs,
8TB의 HBM 메모리, 4억 1,500만
415 million FP32 cores, 13 million tensor cores.
개의 FP32 코어, 1,300만 개의 텐서 코어를 가지고 있습니다.
And this whole thing can do 24 exaflops of compute per second.
이 전체 시스템은 초당 24 엑사플롭의 계산을 수행할 수 있습니다.
That's 24 times 10 to the 18.
24 곱하기 10의 18제곱입니다.
That's a lot of flops.
정말 많은 플롭입니다.
It's a lot of flops, but I guarantee you
많은 연산이 필요하지만, 오늘로부터
five years from today it will not
5년 후에는 그렇게 많은
feel like a lot of flops, which is the even crazier part.
연산이 필요하지 않을 것이라고 보장합니다. 그게 더 미친 부분입니다.
And our goal here is actually to think of this entire block
우리의 목표는 이 24,000개의 GPU
of 24,000 GPUs as one giant supercomputer.
블록을 하나의 거대한 슈퍼컴퓨터로 생각하는 것입니다.
And then the question is, how can we
그리고 질문은, 이 하나의 거대한
train one neural network for months
슈퍼컴퓨터에서 어떻게 한 신경망을 몇
at a time on this one giant supercomputer?
달 동안 훈련할 수 있을까 하는 것입니다.
And train a really gigantic neural network
정말 강력하고 많은 데이터를
that's really powerful, that can soak up tons and tons of data.
흡수할 수 있는 거대한 신경망을 훈련시키는 것입니다.
And that's basically the question and the paradigm
그게 기본적으로 우리가
that we've moved to in deep learning.
딥러닝에서 이동한 질문과 패러다임입니다.
And by the way, I keep saying GPU,
그런데 계속 GPU라고 말하고,
I keep saying NVIDIA because they
NVIDIA라고 말하는 이유는
are the most dominant training architecture and hardware today.
오늘날 가장 지배적인 훈련 아키텍처와 하드웨어이기 때문입니다.
But there are some others that have sprung up.
하지만 다른 것들도 생겨났습니다.
The biggest competitor, I think, right now to NVIDIA training
현재 NVIDIA 훈련 하드웨어의 가장 큰 경쟁자는 Google이라고
hardware is Google.
생각합니다.
Google has their own hardware called
Google은 텐서 처리 장치(TPU)라는
Tensor Processing Units, TPUs.
자체 하드웨어를 가지고 있습니다.
And these are really good.
이것들은 정말 좋습니다.
They've gone through six generations of these already.
이미 여섯 세대를 거쳤습니다.
These are the stats of the v5p TPU, which you
이것은 오늘 Google Cloud에서 임대할 수
can rent in Google Cloud today.
있는 v5p TPU의 통계입니다.
And it's roughly same order of magnitude,
그리고 H100과 비슷한 사양으로
similar specs as the H100 that we just talked about.
대략 같은 규모입니다.
There are some interesting design decisions in the TPU
TPU에는 GPU와는 상당히 다른 흥미로운 설계
that are quite different from the GPUs, which
결정이 있으며, 저는 그것이 매력적이라고
I find fascinating, but we just don't have time
생각하지만 오늘은 그에 대해 이야기할
to get into today.
시간이 없습니다.
And someone was asking, how big are these things?
누군가가 이 것들이 얼마나 큰지 물어보았습니다.
This is an actual picture.
이것은 실제 사진입니다.
Just like GPUs, these TPUs are arranged into pods,
GPU처럼, 이 TPU들은 포드로
and the v5p TPUs can be arranged in pods of up to 8960 chips.
배열되어 있으며, v5p TPU는 최대 8960개의 칩으로 배열될 수 있습니다.
And this is a picture, actually, of a V2 TPU
이것은 256개의 칩만 있는
pod, which has only 256 chips.
V2 TPU 포드의 사진입니다.
So then that gives you a sense of how big these things are,
그래서 이것들이 얼마나 큰지 감을 잡을
each one of those.
수 있습니다.
Then you see there's four racks here.
여기 네 개의 랙이 있습니다.
Those racks are, like I said, maybe about a little bit taller
그 랙은 제가 말했듯이, 제 키보다 약간
than me.
더 큽니다.
And there's four of them side by side for 256 TPU chips.
256개의 TPU 칩을 위해 나란히 배치된 네 개가 있습니다.
And now imagine this thing is going to get a lot bigger
그리고 이제 이 것이 최근 포드에서
in the more recent pods that have up to almost 9,000 chips.
거의 9,000개의 칩으로 훨씬 더 커질 것이라고 상상해 보십시오.
Yes, so Google's Gemini models are almost certainly
네, 그래서 Google의 Gemini 모델은
trained on TPUs.
거의 확실히 TPU에서 훈련되었습니다.
Of course, they don't tell you, but I
물론 그들은 말하지
would be astounded, absolutely astounded if they were not.
않지만, 그렇지 않다면 정말 놀랄 것입니다.
And like I said, the TPUs are actually very good.
그리고 제가 말했듯이, TPU는 실제로 매우 좋습니다.
I assume that most large-scale Google models
대부분의 대규모 Google 모델이 이들에서
are trained on these things, and those
훈련되고 있다고 생각하며, 그것들은
are very competitive models.
매우 경쟁력 있는 모델입니다.
So this is really good training hardware.
그래서 이것은 정말 좋은 훈련 하드웨어입니다.
The difference with NVIDIA is you can't buy it.
NVIDIA와의 차이점은 구매할 수 없다는 것입니다.
The only way you can access TPUs are either by working at Google
TPU에 접근할 수 있는 유일한 방법은 Google에서 일하거나
or by renting them on Google Cloud.
Google Cloud에서 임대하는 것입니다.
But it is very good hardware, and a lot of people
하지만 이것은 매우 좋은 하드웨어이며,
are making use of it, but I think
많은 사람들이 이를
it's still a little bit less popular today than NVIDIA GPUs.
사용하고 있지만, 오늘날 NVIDIA GPU보다 약간 덜 인기 있는 것 같습니다.
And of course, other companies obviously
물론 다른 회사들도 이것이 매우
know that this is a very important thing.
중요한 일이라는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So there's a lot of other companies
경쟁력 있는 훈련
that are trying to build competitive training hardware.
하드웨어를 구축하려는 다른 많은 회사들이 있습니다.
But I think my honest assessment right now
하지만 제 솔직한 평가로는
is that probably NVIDIA and TPUs are the two big ones.
현재 NVIDIA와 TPU가 두 개의 주요 업체일 것입니다.
They're way ahead of everyone else right now,
현재 사용성, 성능,
today, in terms of usability, performance, just like market
시장 점유율 측면에서 모두를 앞서
share.
있습니다.
But there are a lot of others that
하지만 따라잡으려는 많은
are trying to catch up here.
다른 회사들이 있습니다.
Two notable ones are AMD.
주목할 만한 두 개는 AMD입니다.
AMD has been the second major GPU
AMD는 수십 년 동안 두 번째 주요
manufacturer for many decades.
GPU 제조업체였습니다.
They also have a training accelerator called the MI325X.
그들은 MI325X라는 훈련 가속기도 가지고 있습니다.
On paper, it actually has really good stats
서류상으로는 H100과
that are pretty comparable to an H100,
비교할 만한 좋은 성능을
but it just has not had the same impact as the H100 right now.
가지고 있지만, 현재 H100과 같은 영향을 미치지 못하고 있습니다.
AWS also has their own training chip
AWS도 Trainium이라는
that they've developed called Trainium.
자체 훈련 칩을 개발했습니다.
I don't know too much about this one.
이것에 대해서는 잘 모르겠습니다.
I've never tried to use it myself,
저는 직접 사용해본 적이 없지만,
but I know that Anthropic uses it for some of their training.
Anthropic이 그들의 훈련에 사용하고 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
I don't know to what extent their training is entirely
그들의 훈련이 전적으로
Trainium versus GPUs.
Trainium인지 GPU인지 잘 모르겠습니다.
So we should expect to see more.
그래서 더 많은 것을 기대해야 합니다.
But today, I think NVIDIA GPUs are probably the most dominant.
하지만 오늘날 NVIDIA GPU가 아마도 가장 지배적일 것입니다.
And Google TPUs are right there.
그리고 Google TPU도 그 뒤에 있습니다.
They're really good as well but probably not quite
그들도 정말 좋지만 아마도 NVIDIA의
as widely used as GPUs from NVIDIA.
GPU만큼 널리 사용되지는 않을 것입니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
So that's basically part one.
그래서 기본적으로 첫 번째 부분입니다.
What are GPUs?
GPU란 무엇인가요?
How do we arrange them into clusters?
우리는 그것들을 클러스터로 어떻게 배열하나요?
Just give you a sense of the physicality of these machines
우리가 구축하고 훈련하는 이러한 기계의 물리적 특성을
that we're building and training on.
감각적으로 이해할 수 있도록 합니다.
Then the second question is, how do we actually
두 번째 질문은, 수만 개의 GPU로
write algorithms that can make use of this giant GPU cluster
구성된 이 거대한 GPU 클러스터를 활용할 수 있는 알고리즘을 실제로
with tens of thousands of GPUs?
어떻게 작성할 것인가입니다.
It's going to require us to develop
이는 새로운 알고리즘,
new algorithms, new ways of thinking about our compute,
컴퓨팅에 대한 새로운 사고 방식, 신경망을
and new ways of parallelizing and splitting up
병렬화하고 나누는 새로운 방법을
our neural networks.
개발해야 합니다.
So the basic strategy here is going
여기서 기본 전략은 계산을
to be split up your computation.
나누는 것입니다.
These things are giant parallel devices.
이것들은 거대한 병렬 장치입니다.
They have a lot of-- we saw they have a lot of GPUs, a lot of CPU
많은 GPU, 많은 CPU 코어, 많은 GPU
cores, a lot of GPU cores.
코어를 가지고 있습니다.
They can all operate independently,
모두 독립적으로 작동할 수 있으며,
and they can't talk to each other too much.
서로 많이 소통할 수는 없습니다.
If you think about what a computer really does, like,
컴퓨터가 실제로 하는 일을 생각해보면, 고수준에서
at a high level, a computer basically does two things.
컴퓨터는 기본적으로 두 가지 일을 합니다.
It does computation, which is taking input bits
입력 비트를 받아 새로운
and computing new output bits from those,
출력 비트를 계산하는 계산과,
and it does communication, which is taking bits and moving them
비트를 가져와 한 메모리에서
from one bit of memory in one place
다른 메모리로
to some bit of memory in some other place.
이동하는 통신입니다.
And the whole trick is, how do we
그리고 전체 요점은,
make use of all of these multiple scales of memory
전체 클러스터에서 메모리 계층의 여러 규모를
hierarchy across the entire cluster
어떻게 활용하여
to overlap the communication with the computation?
통신과 계산을 겹치게 할 것인가입니다.
And also to split up the computation
또한 계산을 나누고
and parallelize it so that in the process of training
병렬화하여 거대한 신경망을 훈련하는 과정에서
a giant neural network, we have useful work for all
수만 개의 개별 GPU에
of those tens of thousands of individual GPUs.
유용한 작업을 제공하는 것입니다.
All of those millions of individual compute elements,
모든 수백만 개의 개별 계산 요소에
we have useful work for all of them to be doing in parallel,
대해 병렬로 수행할 유용한 작업이 있어야
and then get them to communicate their work to each other
하며, 그런 다음 이 거대한 클러스터에서
in a way that achieves training a giant neural network
거대한 신경망을 훈련하는 방식으로 서로
on this giant cluster.
작업을 소통하게 해야 합니다.
So to that end, one way I like to think about it
그래서 이를 위해 제가 생각하는 한 가지
is there's basically five degrees of parallelism
방법은 사람들이 오늘날 대규모 신경망을 훈련할
that people exploit when training
때 활용하는 기본적으로
neural networks, the large-scale neural networks today.
다섯 가지의 병렬성 수준이 있다는 것입니다.
A lot of this is specific to transformers,
이것의 많은 부분은 트랜스포머에 특화되어
because those are the dominant architecture that people are
있습니다. 왜냐하면 그것들이 대규모 훈련에 사용되는
using for large scale training.
지배적인 아키텍처이기 때문입니다.
So if you think about a transformer,
트랜스포머를 생각해보면,
a transformer is basically a stack of L layers.
트랜스포머는 기본적으로 L개의 레이어로 구성된 스택입니다.
And each one of those L layers is
각 L 레이어는
operating on a three-dimensional tensor
미니배치 차원이 하나인
of size, where one dimension is the minibatch dimension.
크기의 3차원 텐서에서 작동합니다.
We've got a bunch of sequences all
우리는 미니배치에서 작동하는
operating in a minibatch, a sequence dimension.
여러 시퀀스를 가지고 있으며, 시퀀스 차원이 있습니다.
We're operating on sequences or sets of tokens,
우리는 시퀀스 또는 토큰 집합에서 작동하며,
and a dim dimension.
dim 차원이 있습니다.
So each of those tokens itself is a vector with some dimension.
따라서 각 토큰 자체는 어떤 차원을 가진 벡터입니다.
So our transformers are operating
우리의 트랜스포머는 이러한 3차원 텐서에서
on these three-dimensional tensors.
작동합니다.
And they operate through a stack of layers.
그리고 그들은 레이어 스택을 통해 작동합니다.
So that gives us four axes to parallelize on.
그래서 우리는 병렬화할 수 있는 네 가지 축을 갖게 됩니다.
We can parallelize on the layers axis,
우리는 레이어 축에서 병렬화할 수 있으며,
which is pipeline parallelism.
이는 파이프라인 병렬성입니다.
We can parallelize on the batch dimension,
우리는 배치 차원에서 병렬화할 수 있으며, 이는
which is data parallelism.
데이터 병렬성입니다.
We can split on the sequence dimension, which
우리는 시퀀스 차원에서 나눌 수 있으며,
is called context parallelism.
이는 컨텍스트 병렬성이라고 불립니다.
And we can split on that dim dimension, which
그리고 우리는 그 dim 차원에서 나눌 수 있으며,
is called tensor parallelism.
이는 텐서 병렬성이라고 불립니다.
So all of these have funny names.
그래서 이 모든 것들은 재미있는 이름을 가지고 있습니다.
But if you think about it in this way,
하지만 이렇게 생각해보면,
they're basically all different ways
기본적으로 이들은 모두 트랜스포머
of splitting up your computation across these four
내부의 이 네 가지 계산 축을 따라
axes of compute inside your transformer.
계산을 나누는 다양한 방법입니다.
And then we're going to step through each one of these
그리고 우리는 이러한 각각을 더 자세히
in more detail, because there's a lot of interesting nuances
살펴볼 것이며, 분산 훈련의 이러한
with all of these different mechanisms of distributed
다양한 메커니즘에 많은 흥미로운
training.
뉘앙스가 있기 때문입니다.
So the first one is Data Parallelism, or DP.
그래서 첫 번째는 데이터 병렬성, 또는 DP입니다.
And the basic idea here is simple.
여기서 기본 아이디어는 간단합니다.
So remember, when we're training neural networks,
신경망을 훈련할 때 우리는 항상
we're always operating on minibatches of samples.
샘플의 미니배치에서 작동하고 있다는 것을 기억하세요.
We're always taking a minibatch of elements.
우리는 항상 요소의 미니배치를 가져옵니다.
We're computing a loss for every entry in our minibatch,
우리는 훈련 작업에 따라 미니배치의 각
depending on whatever our training task is.
항목에 대해 손실을 계산합니다.
Then we compute a gradient, where the gradient is actually
그런 다음 우리는 그래디언트를 계산하는데,
typically an average of the gradients
그래디언트는 일반적으로 미니배치의 개별
of the losses for the individual elements in the minibatch.
요소에 대한 손실의 그래디언트 평균입니다.
So in most neural network architectures,
대부분의 신경망 아키텍처에서 손실을
the computation of computing the loss
계산하고 그래디언트를
and then computing the gradient is
계산하는 과정은 미니배치의
independent for each of the elements in the minibatch.
각 요소에 대해 독립적입니다.
So this is something that seems trivially parallelizable.
그래서 이것은 명백히 병렬화할 수 있는 것처럼 보입니다.
So the basic idea is that if you can
기본 아이디어는 N개의 예제를 단일
fit a minibatch of N examples on a single GPU
GPU에 맞출 수 있고 M개의 GPU에
and you have access to M GPUs, then
접근할 수 있다면, 우리는 M배의
we're going to train our model with a giant minibatch of M
N개의 예제를 가진 거대한 미니배치로 모델을
times N examples, where we split up that giant minibatch
훈련할 것이라는 것입니다. 이 거대한
into a little tiny, smaller minibatch of N samples
미니배치를 각 GPU에 N개의 샘플로 구성된
that goes on each GPU.
작은 미니배치로 나눕니다.
And if you think about mathematically
그리고 이것이 수학적으로 왜 의미가
why this makes sense, it's because gradients are linear.
있는지 생각해보면, 그래디언트는 선형이기 때문입니다.
So in practice, if you're computing a single scalar
실제로, 단일 스칼라 손실 L을
loss L, which is going to be the average
계산하고 있다면, 이는
of some individual losses computed on each of our--
각 개별 손실의 평균이 될 것입니다.
so these xi,j are all the entries across your entire macro
이 xi,j는 전체 매크로 배치의
batch I guess we'll call it.
모든 항목입니다.
And then the W are the weight matrices of the entire network.
그리고 W는 전체 네트워크의 가중치 행렬입니다.
Then typically the loss that you're
그런 다음 일반적으로
computing at the end of the forward pass
순전파의 마지막에서 계산하는
is an average of the losses on each
손실은 각 개별 미니배치
of the individual minibatch elements.
요소의 손실 평균입니다.
And then if you take the gradient
그리고 네트워크의 가중치에
of the loss with respect to the weights of the network,
대한 손실의 그래디언트를 취하면, 이는 가중치
that's the thing we need to compute in order
업데이트를 수행하기 위해
to make a weight update.
계산해야 하는 것입니다.
Then that is actually going to split.
그런 다음 그것은 실제로 나누어질 것입니다.
Because gradients are linear, you
그래디언트가 선형이기 때문에, 우리는
get to choose in what order do we want to do the sum?
합을 어떤 순서로 할지 선택할 수 있습니다.
Do we want to do the gradient?
그래디언트를 계산할까요?
Do we want to do the averaging?
평균을 계산할까요?
So in particular, it becomes convenient to arrange
그래서 특히, 우리는 N개의
the gradient in this particular formulation
요소에 대한 역전파를 위한
where there's this inner term that we've highlighted
일반적인 내부 항이 파란색으로
in blue, which is basically a normal for backward
강조된 이 특정 공식화에서 그래디언트를 배열하는
pass on N elements.
것이 편리해집니다.
And these can be computed in parallel on different GPUs.
이것들은 서로 다른 GPU에서 병렬로 계산될 수 있습니다.
And then there's an outer sum where
그리고 우리는 운영
we need to take an average of the gradients
중인 M개의 서로
across our M different devices that we're operating on.
다른 장치에서 그래디언트의 평균을 취해야 하는 외부 합이 있습니다.
So that's what's happening from a mathematical perspective.
수학적 관점에서 이것이 일어나고 있습니다.
And we see that this is perfectly mathematically sound.
그리고 우리는 이것이 수학적으로 완벽하게 타당하다는 것을 봅니다.
This is basically exactly the same mathematically
이것은 기본적으로 단일 장치에서
as training on a single device.
훈련하는 것과 수학적으로 정확히 동일합니다.
We've just been clever with our algebra
우리는 대수적으로 영리하게
and changed the order of doing our averages and our summations.
작업하고 평균과 합의 순서를 변경했습니다.
But this is not an approximation.
하지만 이것은 근사가 아닙니다.
This is exactly the same computation
이것은 우리가 단일 대형
as we would have done on a single larger GPU.
GPU에서 수행했을 것과 정확히 동일한 계산입니다.
So what this looks like at the GPU perspective
GPU 관점에서 이것은 M개의
is that we have M GPUs.
GPU가 있다는 것을 의미합니다.
Here I'm showing M equals 3 because that's all that
여기서는 슬라이드에 적절하게 맞는
can sensibly fit on the slide.
3을 보여주고 있습니다.
But think that this is much larger than 3 in practice.
하지만 실제로는 3보다 훨씬 더 큽니다.
Then each one of those GPUs actually maintains
그런 다음 각 GPU는 실제로
its own separate copy of the neural network
최적화기 상태와 그래디언트의
weights of the optimizer state and of the gradients.
신경망 가중치의 별도 복사본을 유지합니다.
So then what we're going to do, each GPU
그래서 우리가 할 것은 각
will load in parallel a different minibatch of data.
GPU가 병렬로 서로 다른 미니배치를 로드하는 것입니다.
Here we're showing each GPU loading
여기서는 각 GPU가 세 개의 요소로 구성된 미니배치를
a minibatch of three elements.
로드하는 모습을 보여주고 있습니다.
And crucially, the different GPUs
그리고 중요한 것은 서로 다른 GPU가 서로 다른
need to load different minibatches of data.
미니배치를 로드해야 한다는 것입니다.
I've had bugs in my code and students
내 코드와 학생 코드에서 버그가 발생했는데,
code, where they actually accidentally load
그들이 실제로 모든 GPU에서 같은
the same minibatch on all the GPUs.
미니배치를 로드하는 실수를 했습니다.
That's not going to help you.
그것은 도움이 되지 않을 것입니다.
That's not going to be good.
좋지 않을 것입니다.
Don't make that mistake.
그 실수를 하지 마세요.
So it's crucially important that your different GPUs actually
서로 다른 GPU가 실제로 서로 다른 미니배치를
load different minibatches of data.
로드하는 것이 매우 중요합니다.
Then each GPU will independently do its own forward pass
그런 다음 각 GPU는 자신의 미니배치 데이터에
on its own minibatch of data to compute its own local loss
대해 독립적으로 순전파를 수행하여 자신의
on its own local minibatch of data.
로컬 손실을 계산합니다.
And these can all operate totally independently.
이 모든 것은 완전히 독립적으로 작동할 수 있습니다.
It does not require any communication between GPUs.
GPU 간의 통신이 필요하지 않습니다.
Then each network will do its own backward pass
그런 다음 각 네트워크는 자신의 로컬 손실에 대한 모델의
to compute the gradient of its own local loss
모든 가중치에 대한 그래디언트를 계산하기
with respect to all the weights of the model.
위해 자신의 역전파를 수행합니다.
And again, this can happen totally independently
그리고 다시, 이것은 각 모델이 기억해야
because each model, remember, has its--
할 독립적인 모델 가중치 복사본을
each GPU has its own independent copy of the model weights.
가지고 있기 때문에 완전히 독립적으로 발생할 수 있습니다.
It can do its own forward backward pass
각 GPU는 완전히 독립적으로 자신의
completely independently.
순전파 및 역전파를 수행할 수 있습니다.
But now after the backward pass is done,
하지만 이제 역전파가 완료된 후,
this is where things get tricky.
여기서 문제가 발생합니다.
Remember, we said we needed to compute
우리는 훈련에 참여하는 모든
an average of those gradients across all the devices that are
장치에서 이러한 그래디언트의 평균을 계산해야
participating in our training.
한다고 말했습니다.
So then we need communication.
그러면 우리는 통신이 필요합니다.
So this is where we do an all reduce operation.
여기서 우리는 올 리듀스 작업을 수행합니다.
And every GPU needs to send its gradients to all the other GPUs.
모든 GPU는 자신의 그래디언트를 다른 모든 GPU에 전송해야 합니다.
So there's two things happening simultaneously.
그래서 두 가지 일이 동시에 발생합니다.
One, each GPU needs to broadcast its gradients to all the GPUs.
하나는 각 GPU가 모든 GPU에 그래디언트를 브로드캐스트해야 합니다.
And then two, each GPU needs to collect the gradients
그리고 두 번째는 각 GPU가 훈련에 참여하는
from all the GPUs that are participating in the training.
모든 GPU로부터 그래디언트를 수집해야 합니다.
So this is an allreduce operation.
이것이 올 리듀스 작업입니다.
And this happens in logarithmic time typically depending
이는 일반적으로 GPU의 수에 따라 로그 시간
on in the number of GPUs.
내에 발생합니다.
But at the end of this allreduce operation,
하지만 이 올 리듀스
then each GPU now has an average of all the gradients
작업이 끝나면 각 GPU는 이제 모든 장치의 그래디언트 평균을
across all the devices.
갖게 됩니다.
So at this point, the communication has happened.
이 시점에서 통신이 이루어졌습니다.
Each GPU now has an identical copy
각 GPU는 이제 모든 장치에서 올
of the gradients that have been all reduced
리듀스된 그래디언트의 동일한
across all the devices.
복사본을 갖고 있습니다.
So now at the beginning of the training iteration,
이제 훈련 반복의 시작에서 우리는 각
we assumed that each GPU had its own independent copy
GPU가 모델 가중치의 독립적인 복사본을 가지고 있다고
of the model weights.
가정했습니다.
Now, at this point, each GPU has its own independent but
이제 이 시점에서 각 GPU는 전체 매크로
identical copy of the gradients across the entire macro
배치 데이터에 걸쳐 독립적이지만 동일한 그래디언트 복사본을
batch of data.
가지고 있습니다.
So now at this point, each GPU can make a weight update
이제 이 시점에서 각 GPU는 자신의 로컬 가중치 복사본에 대해 가중치
on its own local copy of the weights.
업데이트를 수행할 수 있습니다.
And because they started with the same weights
그들은 동일한 가중치로 시작했고 동일한
and they applied the same gradient,
그래디언트를 적용했기
they're going to have the same weights after the local weight
때문에, 산술이 결정론적이라고 가정하면
update, assuming the arithmetic was deterministic.
로컬 가중치 업데이트 후 동일한 가중치를 가질 것입니다.
And also, by the way, then this is really important.
그리고 참고로, 이것은 정말 중요합니다.
Steps 4 and 5 can actually happen in parallel.
4단계와 5단계는 실제로 병렬로 발생할 수 있습니다.
We said that there's actually two things here
우리는 실제로 병렬로 발생할 수 있는 두 가지가
that can happen in parallel.
있다고 말했습니다.
One is the backward pass where each GPU computes
하나는 각 GPU가 그래디언트를 계산하기 위해
its own backward pass to compute gradients,
자신의 역전파를 계산하는 것이고,
and the other is the communication of the gradients
다른 하나는 GPU 간의
across the GPUs.
그래디언트 통신입니다.
And these things in practice will typically
이 두 가지는 실제로 일반적으로
happen simultaneously.
동시에 발생합니다.
So that means that each model will start off
즉, 각 모델은 네트워크의 마지막 레이어에
doing backward pass over the last layer in the network
대해 역전파를 수행하고 자신의 로컬
and then compute its own local gradient.
그래디언트를 계산하기 시작합니다.
Now the model will move its compute
이제 모델은 모델의 두
onto computing backward pass for the second
번째 마지막 레이어에 대한
to last layer of the model.
역전파 계산으로 이동합니다.
And while the compute elements are
그리고 계산 요소들이 두
busy computing the backward pass on the second to last layer,
번째 마지막 레이어에 대한 역전파를 계산하는
then the GPUs will simultaneously
동안, GPU는 동시에 마지막
be doing an all reduce of the gradients of the last layer.
레이어의 그래디언트를 올 리듀스하고 있습니다.
So this means that these things chunk along communication
즉, 이러한 것들은 레이어 L+1에 대한 통신과
for layer L plus 1 and backward pass for layer L.
레이어 L에 대한 역전파를 병렬로 진행합니다.
And they can just chunk along in parallel so that hopefully
그리고 이들은 병렬로 진행될 수 있어,
by the time we've gotten to the end of the network
네트워크의 끝에 도달하고
and by the time the backward pass is done,
역전파가 완료될 때쯤에는 그래디언트가
the gradients have already been all reduced
이미 모든 장치에서 올
across all the devices.
리듀스되었을 것입니다.
And we can make our weight update all at once
그리고 우리는 기다리지 않고 한 번에 가중치
without waiting.
업데이트를 할 수 있습니다.
This is really important because like we said,
이것은 정말 중요합니다. 왜냐하면 우리가 말했듯이
the communication is relatively slow.
통신은 상대적으로 느리기 때문입니다.
So the whole trick in these things
따라서 이러한 것들의
is figuring out ways to hide the communication costs
전체 요점은 통신 비용을 숨기고 계산과 동시에
and do them at the same time as the compute.
수행할 방법을 찾는 것입니다.
The question is, is four or five going to be the bottleneck?
질문은 4단계 또는 5단계가 병목 현상이 될 것인가입니다.
And the answer is yes.
답은 예입니다.
It depends entirely on how fast your device is.
이는 전적으로 장치의 속도에 달려 있습니다.
How big is your model?
모델의 크기는 얼마나 됩니까?
How big is your minibatch?
미니배치 크기는 얼마나 되나요?
How fast is the interconnect between the devices?
장치 간의 인터커넥트 속도는 얼마나 빠른가요?
When you get to this large-scale distributed training,
이 대규모 분산 훈련에 도달하면,
the answer is always, it depends on your situation.
항상 상황에 따라 다르다고 대답합니다.
And you need to benchmark for your situation.
그리고 당신의 상황에 맞게 벤치마크를 해야 합니다.
Oh, why not take M different gradient steps on each of them?
그렇다면 각 모델에서 M개의 다른 그래디언트 스텝을 수행하는 것은 어떨까요?
That's actually a really cool idea.
사실 정말 멋진 아이디어입니다.
There actually was a popular set of algorithms
사실 사람들이 예전에 사용했던 비동기 SGD라는
that people used a while back called asynchronous SGD where
인기 있는 알고리즘 세트가 있었는데, 그들은
they would basically do that, then basically
기본적으로 그렇게 하고,
have a bunch of different model replicas,
여러 개의 독립적인
all take a bunch of independent model steps
모델 스텝을 수행한 다음,
and then try to average them every once in a while.
가끔 평균을 내려고 했습니다.
And those were popular.
그리고 그것들은 인기가 있었습니다.
Actually Google used to do this before they developed the TPU
사실 구글은 TPU 팟을 개발하기 전에 이 방법을
pods.
사용했습니다.
And some of their earlier networks in the early 2010s were
그들의 초기 네트워크 중 일부는 2010년대 초반에
trained in this way.
이 방식으로 훈련되었습니다.
But one, it tends to just be a lot more unstable.
하지만 하나, 이는 훨씬 더 불안정한 경향이 있습니다.
And two, it's very hard to debug and reproduce.
그리고 두 번째, 디버깅과 재현이 매우 어렵습니다.
And it just tends to work a little bit worse.
그리고 그저 조금 더 잘 작동하는 경향이 있습니다.
So it does feel like a more scalable approach.
그래서 더 확장 가능한 접근 방식처럼 느껴집니다.
But in practice, if you can do everything synchronously,
하지만 실제로 모든 것을 동기적으로 수행할 수
then your algorithms are easier to debug, easier
있다면, 알고리즘은 디버깅하기 쉽고,
to understand, easier to reason about.
이해하기 쉽고, 추론하기 쉽습니다.
And basically, if you can get away
기본적으로 동기 그래디언트 업데이트로
with synchronous gradient updates,
해결할 수 있다면, 아마도
it's probably going to work better.
더 잘 작동할 것입니다.
But actually, I would personally not
하지만 사실, 개인적으로는
be too surprised if we see a resurgence of async SGD methods
향후 몇 년 내에 비동기 SGD 방법의 부활을 보더라도 놀라지 않을
in the next couple of years at some point,
것 같습니다. 왜냐하면 그것들이
because I think they are a lot more friendly to distributed
분산 훈련에 훨씬 더 친숙하다고 생각하기
training.
때문입니다.
There's no one computer that can orchestrate all this stuff.
모든 것을 조정할 수 있는 컴퓨터는 없습니다.
All these things are independent devices
모든 장치는 독립적인 장치로
with their own independent stuff.
각자의 독립적인 작업을 수행합니다.
There's no driver that can take a God's eye view
신의 눈으로 모든 단계를 조정할 수 있는
and take those steps.
드라이버는 없습니다.
All that computation has to happen somewhere.
모든 계산은 어딘가에서 이루어져야 합니다.
Oh, great question.
아, 좋은 질문입니다.
I said, as you're overlapping communication and compute,
통신과 계산이 겹칠 때, 이를 위해 코드를 작성해야
do you need to write code for this,
하나요, 아니면
or does the hardware do this automatically?
하드웨어가 자동으로 처리하나요?
You definitely got to write code for this.
확실히 이를 위해 코드를 작성해야 합니다.
The hardware is not smart enough to understand
하드웨어는 당신이 하고자 하는 일을
what you want to do.
이해할 만큼 똑똑하지 않습니다.
The hardware, like we said, it understands these little matrix
하드웨어는 우리가 말했듯이, 이러한 작은 행렬 곱셈
multiply chunks.
조각을 이해합니다.
It understands pretty low-level stuff.
상당히 저수준의 작업을 이해합니다.
Anything that you want to do to schedule that communication,
그 통신을 스케줄링하기 위해 하고자 하는 모든 것은
you need to take care of in software.
소프트웨어에서 처리해야 합니다.
But thankfully for a lot of these common use cases,
하지만 다행히도 이러한 일반적인 사용 사례에 대해
PyTorch ships with it for you.
PyTorch가 이를 제공해 줍니다.
So for example, in this case, there's
예를 들어, 이 경우에는
a PyTorch class called DistributedDataParallel
DistributedDataParallel이라는
that will do this for you and make this happen relatively
PyTorch 클래스가 있어 이를 자동으로 처리하고, 당신이
transparently on top of otherwise
작성한 간단한 PyTorch 코드
straightforward PyTorch code that you've written.
위에서 상대적으로 투명하게 작동하게 합니다.
Although actually that is really interesting
사실 이는 개별 장치와
to contrast with the individual devices,
대조하는 것이 정말 흥미로운데,
because if you're programming an individual GPU in CUDA, which
CUDA에서 개별 GPU를 프로그래밍할 경우,
is NVIDIA's language for programming GPUs,
NVIDIA의 GPU 프로그래밍 언어인
then actually the hardware does take
CUDA에서는 하드웨어가
care of a lot of this async transfer for you automatically.
많은 비동기 전송을 자동으로 처리합니다.
But at the cluster level, it typically doesn't.
하지만 클러스터 수준에서는 일반적으로 그렇지 않습니다.
Then you typically need to do it in software.
그렇다면 일반적으로 소프트웨어에서 이를 수행해야 합니다.
So there actually is a little bit
개별 장치
of interesting asymmetry here between parallelism
수준에서의 병렬성과 클러스터
on the individual device level, where a lot of that
수준에서 소프트웨어로
does happen automatically in hardware versus at the cluster
조정해야 하는 점 사이에
level where it needs to be orchestrated in software.
흥미로운 비대칭이 있습니다.
Yeah, so typically these are heterogeneous systems
네, 일반적으로 이러한 시스템은 서로 다른 프로그래밍
where different parts of the system
언어로 작성된 다양한
are written in different programming languages.
부분이 있는 이질적인 시스템입니다.
So there's going to be low-level device
따라서 실제로 GPU 내부에서
kernels that actually are the code that
실행되는 코드인 저수준
executes inside the GPU.
장치 커널이 있을 것입니다.
And those are typically written in CUDA,
이 커널은 일반적으로
which is it's a C-like language that
CUDA로 작성되며, NVIDIA의
is NVIDIA's language for programming their own GPUs.
GPU 프로그래밍을 위한 C 유사 언어입니다.
But then those individual GPU kernels will get wrapped up.
하지만 이러한 개별 GPU 커널은 포장됩니다.
And you can call those GPU kernels from Python.
그리고 Python에서 이러한 GPU 커널을 호출할 수 있습니다.
And this is basically how PyTorch works.
이것이 기본적으로 PyTorch의 작동 방식입니다.
PyTorch is like a collection of a lot of GPU kernels that can do
PyTorch는 GPU에서 많은 흥미로운 작업을 수행할 수 있는 많은
lots of interesting stuff on the GPU,
GPU 커널의 모음과, 이러한
and then a lot of C++ and Python code that wraps around those GPU
GPU 커널을 감싸고 프로그래밍을 더 사용자 친화적으로 만드는
kernels and makes it more user-friendly to program.
많은 C++ 및 Python 코드로 구성됩니다.
So in this picture, each GPU is computing its own gradients
이 그림에서 각 GPU는 검은색으로 자신의
in black by itself.
그래디언트를 독립적으로 계산하고 있습니다.
And then the gradients in red get
그리고 빨간색 그래디언트는
computed via an allreduce across all the GPUs in parallel.
모든 GPU에서 병렬로 allreduce를 통해 계산됩니다.
Oh, the backward pass at the lower layer
아, 하위 계층의 역전파는
is dependent on the gradients from the previous layer.
이전 계층의 그래디언트에 의존합니다.
But crucially, each GPU is only doing backward pass locally
하지만 중요한 것은 각 GPU가 자신의 미니배치에서만 로컬로 역전파를 수행하고
on its own minibatch.
있다는 것입니다.
So then there's basically two different variants
따라서 이제 각 계층에서 생각해야
of the gradient at each layer that you
할 그래디언트의 두 가지
need to think about now.
변형이 있습니다.
There's the local gradients about the gradient
로컬 그래디언트는 내 미니배치의 로컬
of the local loss of my minibatch with respect
손실에 대한 네트워크 가중치의
to my network weights.
그래디언트입니다.
And there's the global gradient, which
그리고 글로벌
is the derivative of the total loss
그래디언트는 네트워크 가중치에
of the macrobatch with respect to the network weights.
대한 매크로 배치의 총 손실의 도함수입니다.
In order to compute a backward pass,
역전파를 계산하기 위해 각
each GPU only needs the local version
GPU는 자신의 업스트림 그래디언트의
of its upstream gradient.
로컬 버전만 필요합니다.
But then computing the global version of the upstream gradient
하지만 업스트림 그래디언트의 글로벌
requires communication.
버전을 계산하려면 통신이 필요합니다.
So this is data parallelism.
이것이 데이터 병렬성입니다.
And there's actually a bit of problem
그리고 여기에는 약간의 문제가
here, which is, this is a great way
있는데, 이는 GPU 계산을
to parallelize GPU computation.
병렬화하는 훌륭한 방법입니다.
And this was the first way that people
그리고 이것은 사람들이 신경망
started parallelizing GPU computation in neural network
훈련에서 GPU 계산을 병렬화하기 시작한 첫 번째
training.
방법이었습니다.
But we quickly hit a bottleneck on the model size.
하지만 우리는 모델 크기에서 병목 현상에 빠르게 직면했습니다.
So here, remember that each GPU is keeping
따라서 여기서 각 GPU는 모델 매개변수의
its own independent copy of the model parameters,
독립적인 복사본을 유지하고 있으며, 이는
and this becomes a bottleneck when you
정말 큰 모델을 원할
want to have really big models.
때 병목 현상이 됩니다.
So in particular, now each weight in your neural network,
특히 이제 신경망의 각 가중치는 기본적으로
you basically need to keep track of four numbers--
네 개의 숫자를 추적해야 합니다.
the weight itself, the gradient of that weight,
- 가중치 자체, 해당 가중치의 그래디언트, 그리고
and the optimizer state.
옵티마이저 상태입니다.
So if we're using Adam, that's typically
따라서 Adam을 사용하는 경우,
a beta, that's a beta 1 and a beta 2 per parameter
이는 일반적으로 네트워크의 각 매개변수에 대해 베타 1과
in the network.
베타 2입니다.
And sometimes you'll also have an exponential moving average
때때로 모델 매개변수의 지수 이동
of the model parameters as well.
평균도 있을 수 있습니다.
So typically, you'll have four to five scalars
따라서 일반적으로 네트워크의 각 가중치에 대해
that you need to keep track of for every weight
추적해야 할 스칼라가 네 개에서
in your network.
다섯 개가 필요합니다.
And if you're training with 16-bit precision,
그리고 요즘 일반적인 16비트 정밀도로
which is pretty common these days,
훈련하는 경우, 일부는
some of these you'll sometimes keep in higher precision.
때때로 더 높은 정밀도로 유지합니다.
But let's talk about 16-bit as a lower bound.
하지만 16비트를 하한으로 이야기해 봅시다.
Then you need two bytes for each number.
그렇다면 각 숫자에 대해 두 바이트가 필요합니다.
So that means that we need four numbers,
즉, 네 개의 숫자,
2 bytes we need 8 bytes per scalar
네트워크의 각 스칼라에 대해 2바이트가
in the network to keep track of.
필요하므로 8바이트가 필요합니다.
Which means that 1 billion model parameters
이는 10억 개의 모델 매개변수가 모든 것을 저장하는 데
is going to take about 8 gigabytes of GPU memory
약 8기가바이트의 GPU 메모리가
to store all that stuff.
필요하다는 것을 의미합니다.
And we said the whole GPU only has 80 gigabytes
그리고 우리는 전체 GPU가 H100에 대해 80기가바이트의
of memory for an H100.
메모리만 가지고 있다고 말했습니다.
So that means that the biggest model you could ever
즉, 이 시나리오에서 훈련할 수 있는
hope to train in this scenario is something
가장 큰 모델은 약 100억
like 10 billion parameters.
개의 매개변수와 같은 것입니다.
And that's not big enough.
그것은 충분히 크지 않습니다.
We want really big models.
우리는 정말 큰 모델을 원합니다.
We don't want to be constrained by the tyranny of our GPU memory
우리는 훈련할 수 있는 모델의 크기를 결정하는 GPU
size in telling us how big of models we're allowed to train.
메모리 크기의 압박에 의해 제한받고 싶지 않습니다.
So we need to fix this somehow.
그래서 우리는 이 문제를 어떻게든 해결해야 합니다.
And the fix for this is actually relatively easy.
이 문제의 해결책은 사실 상대적으로 쉽습니다.
We need to split the model weights
모델 가중치를 서로 다른
across the different GPUs.
GPU에 분산시켜야 합니다.
So in addition to splitting the batch of data across GPUs,
데이터 배치를 GPU에 분산시키는 것 외에도,
we're also going to split our model weights across the GPUs.
모델 가중치도 GPU에 분산시킬 것입니다.
And this leads to a variant of data parallelism called
이것은 완전 분산 데이터 병렬 처리(Fully Sharded
Fully Sharded Data Parallelism, or FSDP.
Data Parallelism, FSDP)라는 데이터 병렬 처리의 변형으로 이어집니다.
And this is relatively simple.
이것은 상대적으로 간단합니다.
Conceptually what we're going to do
개념적으로 우리가 할
is each model weight in the network, each weight
것은 네트워크의 각 모델 가중치,
Wi we're going to assign it to a owner GPU.
각 가중치 Wi를 소유할 GPU에 할당하는 것입니다.
So each weight will be owned by a unique GPU among the M GPUs
따라서 각 가중치는 우리가 훈련하는 M개의 GPU 중에서 고유한 GPU에
that we're training on.
의해 소유됩니다.
And that the GPU that owns each weight
각 가중치를 소유하는 GPU는
will also be responsible for managing
해당 가중치의 전역
the global gradients for that weight
그래디언트와 옵티마이저
and the optimizer state for that weight.
상태를 관리할 책임이 있습니다.
And typically you would split this up by layer.
일반적으로 이것은 레이어별로 분할합니다.
You're not managing individual scalars.
개별 스칼라를 관리하는 것이 아닙니다.
This W you should think of like the weight
이 W는 신경망의 전체 레이어에 대한
matrix for an entire layer of the neural network.
가중치 행렬처럼 생각해야 합니다.
So now the picture on the right changes a little bit.
그래서 이제 오른쪽 그림이 조금 바뀝니다.
Here we're only showing two GPUs because, spoiler, there's
여기서는 두 개의 GPU만 보여주고 있습니다.
going to be a lot more arrows flying around here
스포일러, 곧 더 많은 화살표가 여기서
in just a moment.
날아다닐 것입니다.
So here we're showing a four layer network
여기서는 두 개의 서로 다른 GPU에
that we're distributing across two different GPUs.
분산된 네 개의 레이어 네트워크를 보여주고 있습니다.
We've assigned the weights for the first two network
첫 번째 두 개의 네트워크 레이어 W1과 W2에 대한
layers W1 and W2.
가중치를 할당했습니다.
Those are owned by GPU 1.
이들은 GPU 1이 소유하고 있습니다.
The weights W3 and W4 are owned by GPU 3 or GPU 2.
가중치 W3와 W4는 GPU 3 또는 GPU 2가 소유하고 있습니다.
So that means that at the start of each batch,
즉, 각 배치의 시작 시 네트워크
the network weights are split up across the GPUs in this way.
가중치는 이렇게 GPU에 분산됩니다.
But it's still data parallelism.
하지만 여전히 데이터 병렬성입니다.
It's still the same basic idea that each GPU
각 GPU는 자신의 독립적인 요소 배치를 로드하고,
is going to load its own independent batch of elements,
그 배치에 대해 전체 전방 및 후방 패스를
do a full forward backward pass on that batch
수행하여 자신의 로컬 그래디언트를 계산한 다음,
to compute its own local gradients,
모든 그래디언트를 축소하고 그래디언트
then all reduce the gradients and take a gradient step.
단계를 수행하는 기본 아이디어는 동일합니다.
Same basic algorithm, but it gets tricky
기본 알고리즘은 동일하지만, 모델 가중치가
now because the model weights are split up.
분할되어 있기 때문에 이제 복잡해집니다.
So here we need to introduce extra communication.
그래서 여기서는 추가 통신을 도입해야 합니다.
So when you're doing fully sharded data
완전히 분산된 데이터
parallelism, now at the beginning of forward,
병렬성을 수행할 때, 이제 전방 패스를
before you start doing the forward pass of the first layer,
시작하기 전에 첫 번째 레이어의 가중치를 소유한
whoever owns that weight for the first layer
사람이 그 가중치 행렬을 훈련
needs to broadcast that weight matrix to all the other GPUs
중인 다른 모든 GPU에 브로드캐스트해야
that you're training on.
합니다.
So in this case, GPU 1 owns W1, so it broadcasts that to GPU 2.
이 경우 GPU 1이 W1을 소유하므로, 이를 GPU 2에 브로드캐스트합니다.
So GPU 2 now has a copy of W1.
그래서 GPU 2는 이제 W1의 복사본을 가집니다.
Now that all the GPUs have a copy of W1,
이제 모든 GPU가 W1의 복사본을 가지므로,
they can run a forward pass through the first layer
네트워크의 첫 번째 레이어를 통해 전방
of the network and compute the activations
패스를 실행하고 첫 번째 레이어의
at the first layer of the network.
활성화를 계산할 수 있습니다.
And now after you run the forward pass,
이제 순전파를 실행한 후, W1을
each GPU that does not own that W1
소유하지 않은 각 GPU는 메모리를 절약하기
is going to delete its local copy of the W1 weight matrix
위해 W1 가중치 행렬의 로컬 복사본을
to save memory.
삭제합니다.
So then after we run the forward pass for the first layer,
따라서 첫 번째 레이어에 대한 순전파를 실행한
we're back in the state where the model weights
후, 모델 가중치가 GPU에
are split up across the GPUs.
분산된 상태로 돌아옵니다.
But now all the GPUs also have an activations in GPU memory
하지만 이제 모든 GPU는 네트워크의 첫 번째 레이어를 실행한
that is the result of running the first layer of the network.
결과로 GPU 메모리에 활성화가 있습니다.
And now it's time to do the second layer,
이제 두 번째 레이어를 수행할 시간이며,
and we do the exact same thing.
동일한 작업을 수행합니다.
So then the GPU that owns the weight matrix for layer 2
따라서 레이어 2의 가중치 행렬을 소유한 GPU는 이를
is going to broadcast that to all the GPUs
훈련 중인 모든 GPU에
that we're training on.
브로드캐스트합니다.
Now they all have their own local copy of W2,
이제 모든 GPU는 W2의 로컬 복사본을 가지고 있으며,
and they can go forward.
앞으로 진행할 수 있습니다.
And by the way, we also have an opportunity
참고로, 여기서 계산과 통신을
to interleave computation and communication here
교차하여 수행할 기회도 있으므로,
as well, so that while we are computing
레이어 i의 순전파를 계산하는
the forward pass for layer i, we can be prefetching
동안 다음 레이어의 가중치를 미리
the weights for the next layer.
가져올 수 있습니다.
So in practice, this will happen in parallel
실제로, 이는 FSDP 실행의
during the forward pass of an FSDP run.
순전파 동안 병렬로 발생합니다.
So then we'll be computing layer 2.
따라서 레이어 2를 계산할 것입니다.
At the same time, we are fetching
동시에 레이어 3의
the weights for layer 3.
가중치를 가져오고 있습니다.
And once we get to layer 3, note that now GPU 1 owns layer 3.
레이어 3에 도달하면, 이제 GPU 1이 레이어 3을 소유하고 있음을 주목하십시오.
So then GPU 1 will be broadcasting the weights
따라서 GPU 1은 훈련 중인 모든 GPU에
to all the GPUs that we're training on.
가중치를 브로드캐스트합니다.
And this will repeat until we've gotten
이 과정은 네트워크의 끝에 도달할
to the end of the network.
때까지 반복됩니다.
And now at the end of the network, then all models,
네트워크의 끝에서 모든 모델은 이제 각 모델이
now we know each model has done a full forward pass,
전체 순전파를 수행하고, 자신의 로컬 배치에
computed its local loss on its own local batch,
대한 로컬 손실을 계산했으며, 모든
and has all the activations for all the layers in memory already
레이어의 활성화를 메모리에 이미 가지고 있음을
for backward.
알게 됩니다.
And now we need to do the same thing in reverse in order
이제 역방향 전파를 계산하기 위해 동일한 작업을
to compute the backward pass.
역으로 수행해야 합니다.
So at the beginning of the backward pass
마지막 레이어의 역방향 전파 시작 시,
for the last layer, whoever owns that last layer weight
마지막 레이어 가중치를 소유한 사람은 이를
will broadcast it to all the devices.
모든 장치에 브로드캐스트합니다.
Once the devices have that weight,
장치가 그 가중치를 받으면,
then they can perform the backward pass.
역방향 전파를 수행할 수 있습니다.
And this whole will do a similar procedure in the backward pass.
이 전체 과정은 역방향 전파에서도 유사한 절차를 수행합니다.
Now there is a little bit of optimization
이제 네트워크의 마지막 레이어에서
we can do on the very last layer in the network, which
최적화할 수 있는 작은 부분이 있는데,
is, have all the GPUs keep the weights
모든 GPU가 마지막 레이어의 가중치를 메모리에 유지하도록
for the last layer in memory.
하는 것입니다.
So this is something that you'll usually do in practice.
이는 일반적으로 실제로 수행하는 작업입니다.
Because at the end, all the GPUs already
왜냐하면 마지막에 모든 GPU가 이미 순전파에서
have a copy of the last layer weights from the forward pass.
마지막 레이어 가중치의 복사본을 가지고 있기 때문입니다.
They'll just keep it in memory.
그들은 단순히 메모리에 유지할 것입니다.
And just because they know they're
그들이 어차피 역방향 전파를
about to reuse it for the backward pass anyway,
위해 재사용할 것이라는 것을 알기 때문에,
so we just won't delete the weights
우리는 마지막 레이어의 가중치를
from the very last layer.
삭제하지 않을 것입니다.
But now there's basically three things
하지만 이제 역방향 전파 동안
that need to happen during the backward pass.
발생해야 할 기본적으로 세 가지 일이 있습니다.
One is that once the GPUs have computed
하나는 GPU가 네트워크의 마지막
the backward pass for their last layer of the network,
레이어에 대한 역방향 전파를 계산한
now that they have a copy of the weights, now at that point,
후, 이제 가중치의 복사본을 가지고
each GPU has computed its own local gradients
있으므로, 각 GPU는 마지막 레이어 가중치에 대한
for its local loss with respect to that last layer weights.
로컬 손실에 대한 로컬 그래디언트를 계산했습니다.
Then we need to communicate those gradients back.
그런 다음 우리는 그 그래디언트를 다시 통신해야 합니다.
And we said that the GPU that owns the weight matrix
그리고 우리는 가중치 행렬을 소유한 GPU가
is also going to be responsible for managing the gradients
해당 가중치 행렬의 그래디언트를 관리할 책임이
for that weight matrix.
있다고 말했습니다.
So now, rather than all reducing the gradients
따라서 이제 데이터 병렬 처리
as we did in the data parallelism case,
사례에서 했던 것처럼 모든
instead we're going to--
그래디언트를 줄이는
just the one GPU that owns that one last layer, weights, is
대신, 마지막 레이어 가중치를 소유한 하나의
going to gather and take a sum across all the local gradients
GPU만이 모든 장치의 로컬 그래디언트를 모으고
across all our devices.
합산할 것입니다.
So in this case, GPU 1 is going to send its last layer
이 경우, GPU 1은 마지막 레이어의
local gradient to GPU 2, which will then
로컬 그래디언트를 GPU 2로 보내고, GPU
have the full gradient dL/dW 4 of the entire macrobatch
2는 마지막 레이어 가중치에 대한 전체 매크로 배치의 그래디언트
with respect to the last layer weights.
dL/dW 4를 가지게 됩니다.
What happens during the downtime?
다운타임 동안 무슨 일이 발생합니까?
You got to get all this stuff happening in parallel.
모든 작업이 병렬로 발생해야 합니다.
So then there's basically three things that
따라서 역방향 전파 동안 기본적으로 세
need to happen during backward.
가지 일이 발생해야 합니다.
During backward, we need to communicate the weights.
역전파 동안 우리는 가중치를 전달해야 합니다.
So whatever GPU owns the layer, owns the weights for that layer
따라서 해당 레이어를 소유한 GPU는 그 레이어의 가중치를
has to broadcast them.
방송해야 합니다.
Two, we need all the GPUs once they get that weight,
둘째, 모든 GPU는 그 가중치를 받으면 해당
you need to compute a backward pass for that layer.
레이어에 대한 역전파를 계산해야 합니다.
And then three, after each GPU computes its backward pass,
셋째, 각 GPU가 역전파를 계산한 후, 그
then it needs to send the result of the gradients with respect
결과를 해당 가중치에 대한
to the weights of that backward pass back
그래디언트로 소유
to the GPU that owns it.
GPU에 다시 보내야 합니다.
And then after that, then once the owner of the weights
그 후, 가중치의 소유자가 전체 그래디언트를 가지게
has that full gradient, then only
되면, 가중치 행렬의 소유자만이
the owner of the weight matrix can now make a gradient update
그 행렬에 대한 그래디언트
on that one weight matrix.
업데이트를 할 수 있습니다.
But I think at this point, we actually
하지만 이 시점에서는 업데이트된
do not need to communicate the updated weight matrix because it
가중치 행렬을 전달할 필요가 없다고 생각합니다. 다음
will get recommunicated to all the GPUs
전방 패스에서 모든 GPU에
on the next forward pass.
다시 전달될 것입니다.
So that's a little bit different from the DP case, maybe.
그래서 이는 DP 사례와는 조금 다를 수 있습니다.
And then basically all of these things
그리고 기본적으로 이러한 모든 일들은
can actually happen in parallel as well.
실제로 병렬로 발생할 수 있습니다.
So we'll repeat this for every layer of the network.
따라서 우리는 네트워크의 모든 레이어에 대해 이 과정을 반복할 것입니다.
And then basically in the steady state of a very deep network,
그리고 기본적으로 매우 깊은 네트워크의 정상
all three of these things will be happening simultaneously.
상태에서 이 세 가지 일이 동시에 발생할 것입니다.
So while we are computing the backward pass for layer L,
우리가 레이어 L에 대한 역전파를 계산하는 동안,
we will be aggregating the gradients
우리는 그래디언트를 집계하고 레이어
and performing a weight update on layer L plus 1.
L+1에 대한 가중치 업데이트를 수행할 것입니다.
And we will be prefetching the weights for layer L minus 1.
그리고 우리는 레이어 L-1에 대한 가중치를 미리 가져올 것입니다.
So I said there's three things that need to happen.
그래서 세 가지 일이 발생해야 한다고 말했습니다.
We need to get the weight, run the backward pass,
우리는 가중치를 가져오고, 역전파를 실행하고, 그래디언트를 집계하고,
and then aggregate the gradient, and update the weight.
가중치를 업데이트해야 합니다.
And these things can all happen in parallel.
이 모든 일들은 병렬로 발생할 수 있습니다.
So basically in general, we'll be
따라서 일반적으로
operating on three consecutive layers and doing all three
우리는 세 개의 연속적인 레이어에서 작업하고, 역전파
of these things in parallel over the course of the backward pass.
과정 동안 이 세 가지 일을 병렬로 수행할 것입니다.
And then as we chunk backwards over the network,
그리고 네트워크를 거슬러
then by the time we-- then hopefully if you were properly
올라가면서, 모든 통신과 계산을 적절히
able to overlap all that communication and computation,
겹치게 할 수 있다면, 역전파가
then by the time you finish your backward pass,
끝날 때쯤 모든 그래디언트가
then all the gradients have already been communicated.
이미 전달되었을 것입니다.
All the GPUs have already finished
모든 GPU는 이미 모든 가중치에
doing their update on all the weights, and we're ready.
대한 업데이트를 완료했으며, 우리는 준비가 되어 있습니다.
And also hopefully your Data Loader that's loading data
또한 데이터를 로드하는 데이터 로더가 비동기적으로
is also happening asynchronously, usually
작동하고 있기를 바랍니다. 보통 서버의
on the CPU cores of our servers.
CPU 코어에서 작동합니다.
So then the CPU is ready with a fresh batch of data
그래서 CPU는 다시 전방으로 나아갈 수 있는 새로운 데이터
to go forward again.
배치로 준비가 되어 있습니다.
So these things are basically parallelization machines.
이러한 것들은 기본적으로 병렬화 기계입니다.
We have a lot of stuff that needs
GPU 내와 GPU
to happen both within a GPU and across GPUs,
간에 발생해야 할 많은 작업이 있으며, 우리는 가능한
and we need to overlap all of that as much as possible.
한 모든 것을 겹치게 해야 합니다.
So we can always feed the GPUs and have
그래서 우리는 항상 GPU에 데이터를
them running on those tensor cores as densely as possible.
공급하고 텐서 코어에서 최대한 밀집하게 실행할 수 있습니다.
So then we're basically ready to do our next batch after that.
그래서 우리는 그 후 다음 배치를 수행할 준비가 되어 있습니다.
So this is great.
그래서 이것은 훌륭합니다.
This is Fully Sharded Data Parallelism.
이것은 완전 분산 데이터 병렬 처리입니다.
And this can get you a long way.
이것은 당신을 멀리 데려갈 수 있습니다.
But there's actually a slightly fancier variant
하지만 사람들이 때때로 사용하는 조금 더 세련된
of data parallelism that people sometimes
데이터 병렬 처리 변형이
use called Hybrid Sharded Data Parallelism, or HSDP.
있습니다. 그것은 하이브리드 분산 데이터 병렬 처리(HSDP)입니다.
And in this case, we're actually going
이 경우, 우리는 개념적으로
to imagine conceptually dividing our GPUs
GPU를 2차원 그리드로 나누는
into a two-dimensional grid.
것을 상상할 것입니다.
So in the previous examples, we said we had N GPUs.
이전 예제에서는 N개의 GPU가 있다고 말했습니다.
And the way that we parallelized our computation was the same.
그리고 우리의 계산을 병렬화하는 방법은 동일했습니다.
We had one axis of parallelization
이전 데이터 병렬 처리 변형에서는
in the previous variants of data parallelism.
하나의 병렬화 축이 있었습니다.
Once we get to Hybrid Sharded Data Parallelism,
하이브리드 샤드 데이터 병렬 처리에
we now are going to have two separate axes of parallelism
도달하면, 이제 동시에 수행할 두 개의
that we will do at the same time.
개별 병렬 축이 생깁니다.
So the first axis is we will do typical FSDP, Fully Sharded Data
첫 번째 축은 우리가 방금 이야기한 대로 전형적인 FSDP, 완전
Parallelism, along one axis that we just talked about.
샤드 데이터 병렬 처리를 수행하는 것입니다.
So we'll have groups of K GPUs.
그래서 K개의 GPU 그룹이 있을 것입니다.
And each group of K GPUs will be doing Fully Sharded Data
각 K GPU 그룹은 우리가 방금 이야기한 완전 샤드 데이터
Parallelism that we just talked about.
병렬 처리를 수행할 것입니다.
So within each group of K GPUs, the model weights
각 K GPU 그룹 내에서 모델 가중치는
will be split across those K GPUs.
해당 K GPU에 걸쳐 분할됩니다.
And they will be interleaving, sending weights and gradients
그들은 서로 간에 가중치와 그래디언트를
back and forth to each other during the forward
주고받으며 전방 및 후방
and backward passes.
패스를 수행합니다.
But we will have now M copies of those K groups
하지만 이제 M개의 K 그룹이 병렬로 작동하게
operating in parallel.
됩니다.
So in this case, we have two groups of four GPUs.
이 경우, 우리는 4개의 GPU 그룹이 두 개 있습니다.
So each group of four GPUs you see
각 4개의 GPU 그룹은 가중치가 4개의
has the weights split across the four GPUs.
GPU에 걸쳐 분할되어 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
But we have the entire setup duplicated a second time
하지만 두 번째 2개의 GPU 그룹에 대해 전체
on a second group of two GPUs.
설정이 두 번째로 복제되었습니다.
And then when you do this, now then they
그리고 이렇게 하면 이제 그룹 간에
do typical data parallelism across the groups.
전형적인 데이터 병렬 처리를 수행합니다.
So within a group, we're going to do forward/backward.
그래서 그룹 내에서는 전방/후방을 수행할 것입니다.
And at the end of the backward, each group
후방 패스가 끝나면 각 그룹은
will have computed its own local gradients.
자신의 로컬 그래디언트를 계산하게 됩니다.
And then after the backward, then each group
그리고 후방 패스가 끝난 후, 각
needs to all reduce the gradients across the groups
그룹은 그룹 간에 그래디언트를 모두 줄여야 하므로
so that we now have the full macro macrobatch gradients
이제 두 그룹 간에 전체 매크로 매크로 배치 그래디언트를
across the two groups.
갖게 됩니다.
And then each group can make a gradient update independently
그런 다음 각 그룹은 매크로 매크로 배치에 대한
once they've received the full gradients for the macro
전체 그래디언트를 받은 후 독립적으로
macrobatch.
그래디언트 업데이트를 수행할 수 있습니다.
So this are called multi-dimensional parallelism,
이것은 다차원 병렬 처리라고 불리며,
because now there's basically two different axes, two
이제 기본적으로 두 개의 다른 축,
different strategies that we're using to parallelize
두 개의 다른 전략을 사용하여
our computation simultaneously.
동시에 계산을 병렬화하고 있습니다.
And why this might be useful is because there's
이것이 유용할 수 있는 이유는 이러한 두
different amounts of communication
가지 종류의 병렬 처리에
required for these two different kinds of parallelism.
필요한 통신량이 다르기 때문입니다.
So if we think about fully sharded parallelism,
완전 샤드 병렬 처리에 대해 생각해보면, 우리는 실제로
we actually need to-- what do we need
-- 완전 샤드 데이터 병렬
to communicate during fully sharded data parallelism?
처리 중에 무엇을 통신해야 하는지 알아야 합니다.
During FSDP, during the forward pass,
FSDP 동안, 전방 패스에서는
remember we were copying the weights all over.
가중치를 복사하고 있었습니다.
During the forward pass, we end up
전방 패스 동안, 우리는
doing a communication of one full copy of the network
네트워크 가중치의 전체 복사본을 통신하게
weights.
됩니다.
Then during the backward pass, we
그런 다음 후방 패스 동안,
need to re communicate the network weights,
우리는 네트워크 가중치를 다시 통신해야
and we also need to communicate the gradients.
하며, 그래디언트도 통신해야 합니다.
So basically when you use fully sharded data parallelism
기본적으로 단일 전방 후방 패스 동안 완전 샤드 데이터 병렬
during a single forward backward pass,
처리를 사용할 때, FSDP
you need to communicate three times
그룹에 참여하는 모든
the network weights across everything participating
것 간에 네트워크 가중치를 세 번
in an FSDP group.
통신해야 합니다.
But when you do normal data parallelism, where
하지만 각 그룹이 가중치의 독립적인 복사본을 유지하는 일반
each group keeps its own independent copy of the weights,
데이터 병렬 처리를 수행할 때는
you only need to all reduce the gradients.
그래디언트만 모두 줄이면 됩니다.
So that means that across multiple data parallelism
즉, 여러 데이터 병렬 처리 그룹 간에는
groups, you only need to communicate the network
전방 후방 패스 동안 네트워크
weights once over a forward backward pass.
가중치를 한 번만 통신하면 됩니다.
And this plays into this idea of multiple levels of hierarchy
이것은 GPU 클러스터 내에서 여러 수준의 계층 구조라는
inside of our GPU clusters.
아이디어와 관련이 있습니다.
So what you might do, for example,
예를 들어, 단일 머신 내에서
is have a GPU server where it has
더 높은 상호 연결을 가진 8개의
eight GPUs with higher interconnect
GPU가 있는 GPU 서버를
inside a single machine.
가질 수 있습니다.
Those might be an FSDP group because it
이들은 FSDP 그룹일 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면
requires more communication inside an FSDP group.
FSDP 그룹 내에서 더 많은 통신이 필요하기 때문입니다.
But then you could have multiple servers
하지만 그런 다음 이 다른
that are on this other axis.
축에 있는 여러 서버를 가질 수 있습니다.
So you have one server with a full copy of the model weights,
그래서 하나의 서버에는 모델 가중치의 전체 복사본이
then another server with another full copy of the model weights.
있고, 다른 서버에는 또 다른 전체 복사본이 있습니다.
And remember, communication across servers
서버 간의 통신은 서버 내의
is going to be slower than communication inside a server.
통신보다 느릴 것이라는 점을 기억하세요.
So then this is our first example of designing algorithms
그래서 이것은 우리가 알고 있는 장치가 연결된 네트워크 토폴로지를
to take advantage of the network topology
활용하기 위해 알고리즘을
that we know our devices are connected into.
설계하는 첫 번째 예입니다.
The question is, would you rather have--
질문은, 당신은 -- 이러한 것들은
these things are impossible to tune.
조정할 수 없다는 것입니다.
It's very, very hard to say.
말하기 매우, 매우 어렵습니다.
And then basically, but once you have data parallelism,
기본적으로 데이터 병렬성이 있으면, DP,
once you have this DP, FSDP, and HSDP,
FSDP, HSDP가 있으면, 이는
this is actually a recipe that can take you a long ways.
실제로 많은 도움이 되는 레시피입니다.
So for example, a model with 100 billion parameters
예를 들어, 1000억 개의 매개변수를 가진 모델은
would take 800 GB of memory to store.
800GB의 메모리를 필요로 합니다.
And if you split that over 80 GPUs,
그리고 이를 80개의 GPU에 나누면,
it only takes 10 gigabytes of memory per GPU.
GPU당 10GB의 메모리만 필요합니다.
So you can have a pretty big model once you have FSDP.
FSDP가 있으면 꽤 큰 모델을 가질 수 있습니다.
But there's another problem that the model activations themselves
하지만 모델의 활성화 자체가 이제 메모리를 채우기 시작하는
now start to fill up memory.
또 다른 문제가 있습니다.
So if we go back to Llama3-405B, it's a transformer with 126
Llama3-405B로 돌아가면, 이는 126개의 레이어,
layers, model dimension of 16,000, sequence length 4,096.
모델 차원 16,000, 시퀀스 길이 4,096인 변환기입니다.
So if you imagine how much GPU memory
순전파 동안 숨겨진 상태를 저장하는 데
it takes to just store the hidden states
GPU 메모리가 얼마나
during the forward pass, that's going to be a lot.
필요한지 상상해 보세요. 그건 상당할 것입니다.
So that's going to quickly cause your GPU
모델과 시퀀스가 정말 커지면
to run out of memory once your models and sequences get really
GPU의 메모리가 금방 부족해질
big.
것입니다.
So that leads to another trick is
그래서 활성화 체크포인팅이라는
called activation checkpointing, which
또 다른 트릭이 있습니다. 이는
means that we're actually not going to store
실제로 모든 활성화를 메모리에
all the activations in memory.
저장하지 않겠다는 의미입니다.
We're going to recompute them during the backward pass.
우리는 역전파 동안 이를 재계산할 것입니다.
So to see how this works, it's useful to think
이것이 어떻게 작동하는지 보려면, 신경망을 다른 방식으로 생각하는
of your neural network in a different way,
것이 유용합니다. 신경망에는
where there's actually two different layers in the neural.
실제로 두 개의 서로 다른 레이어가 있습니다.
Each layer in the neural network does two things.
신경망의 각 레이어는 두 가지 작업을 수행합니다.
It does a forward pass that computes
다음 레이어의 활성화를 계산하는
activations for the next layer.
순전파를 수행합니다.
Then it has a backward pass that computes
그런 다음 상류 기울기와
gradients that take both the upstream gradients
활성화를 모두 사용하는 기울기를 계산하는
and the activations.
역전파를 수행합니다.
So normally, how much compute and memory does this all take?
그렇다면 일반적으로 이 모든 작업에 얼마나 많은 계산과 메모리가 필요할까요?
If we assume that all of these are constant, then typically
모든 것이 일정하다고 가정하면, 일반적으로
a forward backward pass will take 1, 2, 3, 4, four steps
순전파와 역전파는 순전파 동안 1, 2, 3, 4단계가
during forward.
걸립니다.
You'll remember those activations
순전파 동안 이러한 활성화를
during the forward pass.
기억할 것입니다.
Then 1, 2, 3, 4 steps during backward.
그런 다음 역전파 동안 1, 2, 3, 4단계가 걸립니다.
So in a normal forward backward pass,
따라서 일반적인 순전파와 역전파에서는
it takes O(N) compute and O(N) memory for an N layer network.
N 레이어 네트워크에 대해 O(N) 계산과 O(N) 메모리가 필요합니다.
But as we just said, this is going to run out of memory.
하지만 방금 말했듯이, 이는 메모리가 부족해질 것입니다.
So instead what we can do is imagine
따라서 대신 역전파 동안
recomputing the activations during the backward pass.
활성화를 재계산하는 것을 상상할 수 있습니다.
So what that looks like is something like this.
그 모습은 이와 같습니다.
So we'll start with the activations.
활성화부터 시작하겠습니다.
We'll run the first layer and then immediately throw away
첫 번째 레이어를 실행한 다음
the activations for the first--
즉시 첫 번째 레이어의
run the forward pass for the first layer.
활성화를 버립니다.
And then immediately throw away those activations
첫 번째 레이어의 순전파를 실행한 다음 즉시 해당
and so do this four times.
활성화를 버리고 이렇게 네 번 반복합니다.
So now we've gone through the network once,
이제 네트워크를 한 번 통과하여 마지막
got the activations at the last layer.
레이어의 활성화를 얻었습니다.
At this point, we can compute our backward for the last layer,
이 시점에서 마지막 레이어에 대한 역전파를 계산할 수
but now we're kind out of luck.
있지만, 이제 우리는 운이 좋지 않습니다.
We don't have the activations from A3
다음 역전파를 계산하기 위해 A3의 활성화가
to compute the next backward pass, but we can recompute them.
없습니다. 하지만 우리는 이를 재계산할 수 있습니다.
So we recompute them.
그래서 우리는 이를 재계산합니다.
Now we can do the backward pass.
이제 역전파를 수행할 수 있습니다.
Now recompute some more.
이제 좀 더 재계산합니다.
Now do the backward pass.
이제 역전파를 수행하세요.
Now recompute.
이제 다시 계산하세요.
Now do another backward pass.
이제 또 다른 역전파를 수행하세요.
So if you add this all up, this ends up
따라서 모든 것을 합치면, N층의 네트워크에
being N squared compute and constant memory for a network
대해 N 제곱의 계산과 일정한 메모리가 필요합니다.
with N layers, because it's sum N, N minus 1, N minus 2,
왜냐하면 N, N-1, N-2, N-3, 등등을 더하면
N minus 3, blah, blah, blah down to one.
1까지 가기 때문입니다.
That's quadratic time.
이것은 제곱 시간입니다.
And you can split this up.
그리고 이것을 나눌 수 있습니다.
N squared compute is pretty bad for deep networks.
N 제곱 계산은 깊은 네트워크에 대해 꽤 나쁩니다.
So instead, let's not recompute everything.
따라서 대신 모든 것을 다시 계산하지 않도록 합시다.
Let's instead imagine taking a checkpoint of activations
대신 C층마다 활성화 체크포인트를 찍는
every C layers.
것을 상상해 봅시다.
So we'll only recompute within tinier blocks of the network.
그래서 우리는 네트워크의 더 작은 블록 내에서만 다시 계산할 것입니다.
Then in that case, if you take C checkpoints
그런 경우, 네트워크의 과정에서 C번
where you remember your activations C
활성화를 기억하는 C개의
times over the course of your network,
체크포인트를 찍으면, N 제곱을
then it's going to take N squared over C compute and O
C로 나눈 계산과 O의 C
of C memory.
메모리가 필요합니다.
And a pretty common thing to do is
그리고 C를 √N으로
to set C equal to root N, in which case
설정하는 것이 꽤 일반적인 방법이며, 이
this becomes N root N compute and O of root N memory.
경우 N√N 계산과 O의 √N 메모리가 됩니다.
So this is a pretty common way that you
따라서 이것은 더 큰 모델을
can trade-off computation and memory
훈련하기 위해 계산과 메모리의 균형을
to train even bigger models.
맞출 수 있는 꽤 일반적인 방법입니다.
OK.
좋아요.
So now at this point, once we have
이제 FSDP, 활성화
FSDP, activation checkpointing, HSDP, we can do a lot of damage
체크포인팅, HSDP가 있으면 많은 일을 할 수
here.
있습니다.
We can start to train some really big models.
정말 큰 모델을 훈련하기 시작할 수 있습니다.
And the recipe for that is basically as following.
그에 대한 레시피는 기본적으로 다음과 같습니다.
So your scaling recipe that will take you
여기서 꽤 멀리 나아갈 수 있는
quite a long way from here is first, use data parallelism,
스케일링 레시피는 먼저 데이터 병렬성을 사용하고, 그냥 원시
just raw data parallelism, roughly up to 128 GPUs
데이터 병렬성을 사용하여 대략 128개의 GPU와 대략 10억
and roughly up to models of around a billion parameters.
개의 매개변수를 가진 모델까지입니다.
You can just do normal data parallelism
이 크기의 모델에 대해서는 일반 데이터
for models of this size.
병렬성을 사용할 수 있습니다.
It tends to work pretty well.
상당히 잘 작동하는 경향이 있습니다.
And another thing that you almost always
그리고 거의 항상 GPU 메모리를
want to set the local batch size per GPU
최대화하기 위해 각 GPU의 로컬 배치 크기를
to max out the GPU memory.
설정하는 것이 좋습니다.
That's almost always the right thing to do.
거의 항상 올바른 선택입니다.
And then once your model starts to get big,
그리고 모델이 커지기 시작하면,
then the model itself will take up
모델 자체가 GPU 내부에서
a lot of memory inside your GPU.
많은 메모리를 차지하게 됩니다.
So that will start to give you problems.
그래서 문제가 발생하기 시작합니다.
So it depends on how much memory your GPU has,
따라서 GPU의 메모리 용량과 인터커넥트 속도에
how fast your interconnects are.
따라 다릅니다.
But in general, once your model starts
하지만 일반적으로 모델이 10억
to be more than a billion parameters,
개의 매개변수를 초과하기
that's when you want to start thinking
시작하면, 데이터
about switching from data parallelism
병렬성에서 완전 분산 데이터
to fully sharded data parallelism.
병렬성으로 전환하는 것을 고려해야 합니다.
And then at this point, you can scale up quite a bit,
그리고 이 시점에서 꽤 많이 확장할 수 있지만,
but then you'll run into the memory bottleneck
활성화에 대한 메모리 병목 현상에
for your activations.
직면하게 됩니다.
And that's when you turn on activation check pointing.
그때 활성화 체크포인팅을 켭니다.
Activation check pointing sucks because it
활성화 체크포인팅은 모든 것을
makes everything a lot slower, but it does let
훨씬 느리게 만들기 때문에 좋지
you train much bigger models.
않지만, 훨씬 더 큰 모델을 훈련할 수 있게 해줍니다.
And this will scale up to several hundred GPUs.
그리고 이것은 수백 개의 GPU까지 확장됩니다.
And then there's some point, usually depending
그리고 클러스터 토폴로지에
on your cluster topology, maybe around 256 GPUs, maybe
따라 다르지만, 보통 256개의 GPU
around 512 GPUs, once you get to on the order
또는 512개의 GPU 정도에서
of multiple hundreds of devices, then FSDP becomes too expensive.
여러 백 개의 장치에 도달하면 FSDP가 너무 비쌉니다.
And you need to start switching to HSDP.
그때 HSDP로 전환하기 시작해야 합니다.
And then this is basically going to let you get up
그리고 이것은 대략 수십억 개의
to models that are roughly tens of billions of parameters,
매개변수를 가진 모델에 도달할 수 있게 해주며,
training on maybe a thousand GPUs
아마도 천 개의 GPU에서 꽤 긴 시퀀스
on pretty long sequence lengths.
길이로 훈련할 수 있습니다.
So that's pretty good.
그래서 꽤 좋습니다.
But if you have maybe more than thousand GPUs,
하지만 만약 천 개 이상의 GPU와 500억 개
more than 50 billion parameter models,
이상의 매개변수를 가진 모델,
sequence lengths more than 10,000 or so, this is when you
10,000 이상 시퀀스 길이가 필요하다면, 이때는 더 고급
need to turn to these more advanced strategies--
전략인 컨텍스트 병렬 처리,
context parallelism, pipeline parallelism,
파이프라인 병렬 처리 또는 텐서
or tensor parallelism.
병렬 처리로 전환해야 합니다.
And then there's a big question.
그리고 큰 질문이 있습니다.
It's like, oh, my God.
오, 세상에.
There's a lot of knobs to tune here.
여기 조정해야 할 것이 많습니다.
How am I supposed to optimize this?
어떻게 최적화해야 할까요?
I need to set the global batch size, the local batch
전역 배치 크기, 로컬 배치 크기,
size, the HSDP dimension, the FSDP dimension,
HSDP 차원, FSDP 차원, 얼마나
how much to recompute.
재계산할지를 설정해야 합니다.
I'm lost here.
여기서 길을 잃었습니다.
What do I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
There's so many knobs, I don't know what do I do?
조정해야 할 것이 너무 많아서 무엇을 해야 할지 모르겠습니다.
The answer is to optimize a very important metric
답은 모델 플롭스 활용도(MFU)라는 매우
called Model Flops Utilization, MFU.
중요한 지표를 최적화하는 것입니다.
Whenever you get lost in the sea of GPU parallelism,
GPU 병렬 처리의 바다에서 길을 잃을 때마다, 모델 플롭스
Model Flops Utilization is your guiding light.
활용도가 당신의 길잡이입니다.
Follow this, it will tell you what
이것을 따르세요, 그러면 훈련
to do to optimize your training stack.
스택을 최적화하기 위해 무엇을 해야 할지 알려줄 것입니다.
But before we get to Model Flops Utilization,
하지만 모델 플롭스 활용도에 도달하기 전에
we need to talk about Hardware Flops Utilization.
하드웨어 플롭스 활용도에 대해 이야기해야 합니다.
So remember we said in theory, an H100 can
이론적으로 H100은 텐서 코어에서
do 989.4 TFLOPs per second of compute on the tensor cores.
초당 989.4 TFLOP의 연산을 수행할 수 있다고 했습니다.
But that's theoretical.
하지만 이것은 이론적입니다.
How much can you actually get?
실제로 얼마나 얻을 수 있을까요?
The question is, how much can you actually
질문은 실제로 얼마나
achieve in practice?
달성할 수 있는가입니다.
And that's the metric of Hardware Flops Utilization.
그리고 그것이 하드웨어 플롭스 활용도의 지표입니다.
You're running some compute on the device.
장치에서 일부 연산을 수행하고 있습니다.
How much compute do you actually realize
이론적 최대치에서 실제로 얼마나
of that theoretical maximum?
많은 연산을 실현하고 있습니까?
And this is not hard to do.
이것은 어렵지 않습니다.
You can write a couple lines of PyTorch
몇 줄의 PyTorch 코드를
code and just like benchmark this.
작성하고 이를 벤치마크할 수 있습니다.
So this is a benchmark that I wrote that I ran on an H100
이것은 제가 어제 H100에서 실행한
yesterday.
벤치마크입니다.
And you can see what it does is basically x-axis.
그리고 이것이 하는 일은 기본적으로 x축입니다.
It just does dense matrix multiply in a loop
루프에서 밀집 행렬 곱셈을 수행하고, 그 다음
and then times how long did the matrix multiply happen?
행렬 곱셈이 얼마나 걸렸는지 측정합니다.
How long did the matrix multiply take?
행렬 곱셈이 얼마나 걸렸는지 알 수 있습니다.
We can compute how many flops a matrix multiply takes.
행렬 곱셈이 얼마나 많은 플롭스를 소모하는지 계산할 수 있습니다.
Then on the x-axis, we're plotting the size of our matrix
그런 다음 x축에서 행렬의 크기를 512에서
going from 512 up to 32,000.
32,000까지 플로팅하고 있습니다.
And then the y-axis is this hardware flops utilization,
y축은 하드웨어 플롭스 활용도로, 기본적으로
which is basically the fraction of the theoretical maximum
이러한 행렬 곱셈에서 우리가
throughput of the device that we actually realize
실제로 실현한 장치의 이론적 최대
from these matrix multiplies.
처리량의 비율입니다.
And you can see that on this pretty straightforward PyTorch
그리고 이 꽤 간단한 PyTorch 루프에서,
loop, we're getting about 80% HFU on an H100 once we get
우리는 8,000 x 8,000의 대형 행렬 곱셈에
to large matrix multiplies of around 8,000 by 8,000.
도달하면 H100에서 약 80% HFU를 얻고 있습니다.
So that's pretty good.
그래서 꽤 괜찮습니다.
But the problem is that HFU does not
하지만 문제는 HFU가 모델이
account for all the other stuff that your model needs to do.
해야 할 다른 모든 것을 고려하지 않는다는 것입니다.
We're maybe doing activation computation.
우리는 아마도 활성화 계산을 하고 있습니다.
We're maybe running some other models on the side.
우리는 아마도 다른 모델을 옆에서 실행하고 있습니다.
We're maybe doing data loading, data augmentation.
우리는 아마도 데이터 로딩, 데이터 증강을 하고 있습니다.
There's a lot of other stuff your GPU
GPU가 원시 모델에서 순전파와
is doing other than just forward backward on your raw model.
역전파 외에 수행하는 다른 작업이 많습니다.
And that's where we move from Hardware Flops Utilization
그래서 우리는 하드웨어 플롭스 활용도에서
to Model Flops Utilization.
모델 플롭스 활용도로 이동합니다.
So Model Flops Utilization is basically
모델 플롭스 활용도는 기본적으로
saying, what fraction of the GPU's theoretical TFLOPs
GPU의 이론적 TFLOP 중 몇 퍼센트가 내 모델의
are being used for forward backward in my model?
순전파와 역전파에 사용되고 있는지를 말합니다.
And this is the thing you always want to optimize for.
그리고 이것이 항상 최적화하고 싶은 것입니다.
So then to make this more concrete, you basically compute,
그러면 이를 더 구체적으로 만들기 위해,
based on your model architecture,
모델 아키텍처,
the size of the number of the layers, the size of the layers
레이어 수, 레이어 크기를
you compute, how many flops does it
기반으로 전체 순전파
take to do a full forward backward
및 역전파를 수행하는
pass of your architecture on your minibatch of data?
데 필요한 플롭 수를 계산합니다.
Then you look up somewhere, the peak theoretical throughput
그런 다음 실행 중인 장치의 이론적 최대 처리량을
of the device you're running on.
어디선가 찾아봅니다.
And then you divide those two.
그리고 그 두 수를 나눕니다.
And that tells you how long should a full forward backward
그것은 이론적 최대 처리량을 달성할 경우
pass take if you were achieving the theoretical maximum
전체 순전파 및 역전파가 얼마나 걸려야
throughput of the device?
하는지를 알려줍니다.
That's the theoretical fastest you could ever do a forward
그것이 모델에서 순전파 및 역전파를 수행할
backward pass on your model.
수 있는 이론적 최속입니다.
Then you actually time a forward backward pass of your model.
그런 다음 실제로 모델의 순전파 및 역전파를 시간 측정합니다.
Your training loop is doing all this other stuff.
훈련 루프는 이 모든 다른 작업을 수행하고 있습니다.
It's doing data loading.
데이터 로딩을 하고 있습니다.
It's doing augmentation.
증강을 하고 있습니다.
It's doing communication.
통신을 하고 있습니다.
It's doing maybe activation checkpointing.
아마도 활성화 체크포인팅을 하고 있습니다.
So it's doing recomputation, doing backward.
그래서 재계산을 하고 역전파를 하고 있습니다.
Your training loop is doing a lot of stuff.
훈련 루프는 많은 작업을 수행하고 있습니다.
Just times see how long it actually takes.
실제로 얼마나 걸리는지 시간을 측정합니다.
And then divide those two numbers.
그리고 그 두 숫자를 나눕니다.
That gives you a number between 0 and 1, which is like,
그것은 0과 1 사이의 숫자를 제공합니다.
what fraction of that theoretical maximum
즉, 훈련 루프에서 이론적 최대의
are you actually achieving in your training loop?
몇 퍼센트를 실제로 달성하고 있는지를 나타냅니다.
And that's your MFU, your Model Flops Utilization.
그것이 MFU, 즉 모델 플롭스 활용도입니다.
And again, we can benchmark this with some relatively simple
그리고 다시, 우리는 이것을 상대적으로 간단한 PyTorch 코드로
PyTorch code.
벤치마킹할 수 있습니다.
Here's an example running forward backward
여기 ReLU 비선형성을
on just a short multi-layer perceptron with a ReLU
가진 짧은 다층 퍼셉트론에서 순전파 및 역전파를 실행하는 예가
nonlinearity and with really big, with really wide MLP layers
있습니다. 매우 크고 넓은 MLP 레이어와 거대한
and a gigantic batch size on a single H100.
배치 크기를 가진 단일 H100에서 실행됩니다.
This is getting around 50% MFU.
이것은 약 50% MFU를 달성하고 있습니다.
And then in general, whenever you're
그리고 일반적으로 분산 훈련을
trying to tune knobs for distributed training,
위한 조정 노브를 조정할 때는 항상
you always want to try to tune whatever
MFU를 극대화하기 위해 조정할 수
knobs you can to maximize MFU, because that's the one
있는 모든 노브를 조정하려고 합니다. 왜냐하면
metric that we typically care about when trying to optimize
훈련 처리량을 최적화할 때 우리가 일반적으로
training throughput.
중요하게 여기는 유일한 지표이기 때문입니다.
And in general, an MFU these days generally above 30%
그리고 일반적으로 요즘 MFU가 30% 이상이면 꽤
is pretty good.
괜찮습니다.
If you're way under 30%, you've probably
30% 이하라면 아마도 어딘가에
got some gigantic bottleneck somewhere
거대한 병목 현상이 있고 무언가
and something is going wrong.
잘못되고 있는 것입니다.
And above 40% is pretty, pretty excellent.
40% 이상은 꽤, 꽤 훌륭합니다.
And that's basically state of the art.
그리고 그것은 기본적으로 최첨단입니다.
And here's some numbers that we can
그리고 여기서 몇몇 논문에서 가져올
pull from a couple of papers.
수 있는 숫자들이 있습니다.
In particular, this is that Llama3-405B paper
특히, 우리가 이야기했던 Llama3-405B
that we talked about.
논문입니다.
In their final training step, they have a couple different
그들의 최종 훈련 단계에서는 8,
variants of their training phases where they train
000에서 16,000개의 GPU를
on between 8,000 and 16,000 GPUs simultaneously.
동시에 사용하는 여러 가지 훈련 단계 변형이 있습니다.
And across that, they're getting MFUs roughly in the high 30s,
그 결과, 대략 30대 후반에서 40대 초반의 MFU를 얻고
low 40s.
있습니다.
And that's pretty good.
그것은 꽤 좋습니다.
You're never going to get really much
H100에서는 그보다 훨씬
higher than that on an H100.
더 높은 수치를 얻기 어렵습니다.
And actually, paradoxically, more recent devices sometimes
실제로, 역설적으로, 최신 장치에서는 때때로 MFU가 더
get worse MFUs.
나빠질 수 있습니다.
So on the previous generation devices, the H100s,
이전 세대 장치인 H100에서는 때때로 50%
you could sometimes get MFUs above 50%.
이상의 MFU를 얻을 수 있었습니다.
And the reason for that is because GPUs
그 이유는 GPU가 더 빨라지고
are getting faster, faster than they are getting faster
있지만, 통신 속도가 그만큼 빨라지지
at communicating.
않기 때문입니다.
So when we move from the A100 to the H100,
A100에서 H100으로 이동할 때,
we got roughly a 3x improvement in the theoretical throughput
이론적인 처리량에서 대략 3배의 개선을
of the compute, but we only got a 2x improvement
얻었지만, 이론적인 메모리 대역폭에서는
in the theoretical memory bandwidth.
2배의 개선만 있었습니다.
So there's this growing gap between making
GPU가 매우 빠르게 빨라지고 있지만, GPU
GPUs are getting faster really fast,
간의 통신을 확장하는 것은
but it's harder to scale the communication between the GPUs.
더 어려워지는 격차가 커지고 있습니다.
And as a result, we tend to sometimes get worse MFAs
그 결과, 최신 세대 장치에서는 실제로 MFAs가
actually on more recent generations of devices.
더 나빠지는 경향이 있습니다.
And I intentionally I wanted to spend most of the time
나는 의도적으로 그 점들에 대부분의 시간을 할애하고
on those points, because those are the ones
싶었습니다. 왜냐하면 여러분이 실제로
that you guys are probably going to use in practice.
사용할 가능성이 높은 것들이기 때문입니다.
I don't think anyone in this room likely has access
이 방에 있는 누구도 10,000 GPU 클러스터에
to a 10,000 GPU cluster.
접근할 가능성은 낮다고 생각합니다.
If you do, come talk to me after class.
만약 그렇다면, 수업 후에 저에게 이야기해 주세요.
I would love to be your friend.
친구가 되고 싶습니다.
So those are the ones that you're
그래서 여러분이 실제로
likely to encounter in practice, like, up
마주칠 가능성이 있는 것들은
to many hundreds of GPUs.
수백 개의 GPU까지입니다.
But there are these other ones that I just like.
하지만 제가 좋아하는 다른 것들도 있습니다.
There are slides here that I think are pretty nice,
여기 꽤 괜찮은 슬라이드가 있지만, 전체
but it's OK if we don't go through the full details
세부 사항을 다루지 않아도
of these.
괜찮습니다.
You can check it offline.
오프라인에서 확인할 수 있습니다.
So we said context parallelism is basically
우리는 맥락 병렬성이 기본적으로 시퀀스
splitting on the sequence dimension.
차원에서 나누는 것이라고 말했습니다.
So we said transformers are operating on sequences.
우리는 변환기가 시퀀스에서 작동한다고 말했습니다.
And basically the idea is you've got a long sequence.
기본적으로 아이디어는 긴 시퀀스가 있다는 것입니다.
Make different GPUs handle different parts of the sequence.
서로 다른 GPU가 시퀀스의 서로 다른 부분을 처리하게 합니다.
And if you recall, your transformer block,
변환기 블록을 기억하신다면,
this is actually easy for large parts of the transformer
LayerNorm, FFN, MLP
because the LayerNorm, the FFN, MLP,
및 잔여 연결은 시퀀스 전반에 걸쳐 독립적으로
and the residual connections, those
작동하므로 변환기의
all operate independently across the sequence anyway.
큰 부분에 대해서는 실제로 쉽습니다.
So it's relatively straightforward
따라서 시퀀스
to ask to chunk up that computation across the sequence
차원에서 그 계산을 청크로 나누는
dimension.
것은 상대적으로 간단합니다.
I mean, it does get a little bit hairy inside the MLP
MLP 내부에서는 약간 복잡해지긴 하지만, 그
because there are weights in there.
안에 가중치가 있기 때문입니다.
So you have to have some all reduce of the gradients
따라서 데이터 병렬성 사례에서 했던
like we did in the data parallelism cases.
것처럼 그래디언트를 모두 줄여야 합니다.
The attention is where things get
주의는 시퀀스 병렬성에서
hairy for sequence parallelism.
복잡해지는 부분입니다.
Because if you remember attention,
왜냐하면 주의를 기억하신다면,
we need to compute these all pairs interaction
시퀀스 내의 모든 쌍의 요소
between every pair of elements inside the sequence.
간의 상호작용을 계산해야 하기 때문입니다.
The QKV projection is easy, because that's
QKV 프로젝션은 쉽습니다.
trivially parallelizable over the sequence,
왜냐하면 시퀀스에 대해 자명하게 병렬화할
but that core attention matrix, that actually gets pretty tricky
수 있지만, 실제로 병렬화하기는 꽤 까다로운
to parallelize.
핵심 어텐션 매트릭스가 있습니다.
The first version of this that people developed
사람들이 개발한 첫 번째
was called ring attention, where you basically
버전은 링 어텐션이라고 불리며,
take that full attention matrix, chunk it up into blocks,
기본적으로 전체 어텐션 매트릭스를 블록으로
and then have your GPUs work on those blocks
나누고, 그런 다음 GPU가 올바른 순서로 이
independently in parallel in the right order
블록에서 독립적으로 병렬
to make sure everything works out.
작업을 하도록 합니다.
There's a lot of details in there.
그 안에는 많은 세부 사항이 있습니다.
You can check out the paper for more details.
더 많은 세부 사항은 논문을 확인해 보세요.
The second, which is a little bit conceptually easier,
두 번째는 개념적으로 조금 더 쉬운
is called Ulysses attention, where you
Ulysses 어텐션이라고 하며, 여기서는 헤드에
do parallelism over the heads.
대해 병렬성을 수행합니다.
So remember in a transformer, you're almost always
변환기에서 거의 항상 여러 어텐션
doing multi-head attention where you're
매트릭스에 대해 병렬로
computing attention over multiple attention matrices
어텐션을 계산하는 멀티 헤드 어텐션을 수행하고 있다는
all in parallel.
점을 기억하세요.
So in Ulysses attention, we're going
Ulysses 어텐션에서는
to parallelize the computation of that core attention operator.
그 핵심 어텐션 연산자의 계산을 병렬화할 것입니다.
Parallelize that overheads, and then everything else,
그 오버헤드를 병렬화하고,
all other parts of the transformer
변환기의 다른 모든
are parallelized over the sequence dimension.
부분은 시퀀스 차원에 대해 병렬화됩니다.
And as an example, this context parallelism
예를 들어, 이 컨텍스트 병렬성은 시퀀스 길이를
becomes important once you scale up your sequence length
상당히 크게 확장할 때
to be quite large.
중요해집니다.
So if we go back to this example of Llama3 pretraining,
Llama3 사전 훈련의 예로 돌아가면,
they actually train the model in two stages.
실제로 모델을 두 단계로 훈련합니다.
The first stage they go sequence length of 8,000 with no context
첫 번째 단계에서는 컨텍스트 병렬성 없이 시퀀스 길이를 8,
parallelism whatsoever.
000으로 설정합니다.
And then they have a second stage of training where they
그런 다음 시퀀스 길이를 130,000으로
crank the sequence length up to 130,000.
늘리는 두 번째 훈련 단계를 가집니다.
And at that point, they do 16 way context parallelism.
그 시점에서 16배 컨텍스트 병렬성을 수행합니다.
So that means that each of those 131,000 long sequences has 16
즉, 131,000 길이의 각 시퀀스는 16개의 GPU가 하나의 시퀀스에서
GPUs operating on one sequence in parallel.
병렬로 작동하고 있다는 의미입니다.
And that's like saying the batch size is 1/16, because now,
이는 배치 크기가 1/16이라는 것과 같으며,
each batch, each GPU is working on less than one element.
이제 각 배치, 각 GPU는 하나의 요소보다 적은 작업을 하고 있습니다.
So that's context parallelism.
이것이 컨텍스트 병렬성입니다.
Pipeline parallelism.
파이프라인 병렬성.
We're going to split across the layers dimension.
우리는 레이어 차원에서 나눌 것입니다.
Intuitively what you want to do, you have a network
직관적으로 하고 싶은 것은 여러 레이어가 있는 네트워크를
with a bunch of layers.
가지는 것입니다.
And we're going to just divide the layers across the GPUs.
그리고 우리는 GPU에 레이어를 나누기만 하면 됩니다.
That's actually a very intuitive thing to do.
사실, 이것은 매우 직관적인 일입니다.
The problem is that there's sequential dependencies?
문제는 순차적 의존성이 있다는 것입니다.
Because each GPU, it needs the activations
각 GPU는 포워드 패스를 계속 실행하기
from the previous GPU to continue
위해 이전 GPU의 활성화를
running the forward pass.
필요로 합니다.
And during the backward pass, I need the gradients
역방향 패스 동안, 역방향 패스를
from the upstream layers in order
계산하기 위해 상류 레이어의
to compute the backward pass.
그래디언트가 필요합니다.
So we can draw a diagram like this, where the vertical axis
그래서 이렇게 다이어그램을 그릴 수 있습니다. 수직 축은
are GPUs 1 to 4.
GPU 1에서 4까지입니다.
The horizontal axis is what happens over the course of time.
수평 축은 시간 경과에 따른 상황입니다.
So you can see that GPU 1 runs forward, then passes
GPU 1이 포워드를 실행한 다음 활성화를 GPU 2에 전달하고, GPU
the activations to GPU 2, which passes activations to GPU 3,
2가 GPU 3에 활성화를 전달하고, GPU 3이 GPU 4에
which passes activations to GPU 4.
활성화를 전달하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
GPU 4 is lucky.
GPU 4는 운이 좋습니다.
It can do forward backward all at once,
한 번에 포워드와 백워드를 모두 수행한
then pass gradients back to GPU 3, back to GPU 2, back to GPU 1.
다음 그래디언트를 GPU 3, GPU 2, GPU 1로 다시 전달할 수 있습니다.
So from this graph, that's obviously really, really bad,
그래프에서 보듯이, 이는 정말로 나쁜 상황입니다. 왜냐하면 GPU가
because the GPUs are mostly sitting idle.
대부분 유휴 상태로 있기 때문입니다.
And in fact, if you have N GPUs, you're only getting useful work
실제로 N개의 GPU가 있다면, 그들로부터 유용한 작업을 얻는
out of them 1/N of the time.
것은 1/N의 시간만 가능합니다.
So that means that if we had eight-way pipeline parallelism,
즉, 8배 파이프라인 병렬성이 있다면, 그
your maximum possible MFU at that point
시점에서 최대 가능한 MFU는
is like 12%, which is terrible.
약 12%로, 이는 끔찍합니다.
So that's really bad.
그래서 그건 정말 나쁘다.
And by the way, there's a cute name.
그리고 참고로, 귀여운 이름이 있다.
These are sometimes called the bubble,
이것들은 가끔 버블이라고
is like that chunk of where GPUs are waiting for work.
불리며, GPU가 작업을 기다리는 그 덩어리와 같다.
And they're like waiting around for the communication.
그리고 그들은 통신을 기다리고 있다.
So the trick in pipeline parallelism
파이프라인 병렬 처리의 요점은
is to shrink the bubble.
버블을 줄이는 것이다.
You want to have less bubble.
버블을 줄이는 것이 좋다.
And the way that we do that is running multiple microbatches
우리가 이를 수행하는 방법은 여러 개의 마이크로 배치를
simultaneously.
동시에 실행하는 것이다.
So now rather than running one batch
이제 모든 GPU를 통해 데이터를 한
of data through all the GPUs forward and backward,
배치씩 순방향과 역방향으로
we're going to have multiple batches of data in play
실행하는 대신, 여러 개의 데이터
simultaneously and shuttle these things
배치를 동시에 사용하고 이들을
across the GPUs in parallel.
GPU 간에 병렬로 이동시킬 것이다.
So there's a lot of different interesting patterns
이것을 위해 시도할 수 있는 다양한
you can try to design for this.
흥미로운 패턴이 있다.
But here's a relatively simple one,
하지만 여기에는 상대적으로 간단한
where we have four-way pipeline parallelism.
패턴이 있다. 네 방향 파이프라인 병렬 처리이다.
So there's four GPUs that are all working in parallel.
네 개의 GPU가 모두 병렬로 작업하고 있다.
And then we have four batches of data that are all
그리고 동시에 활성화된 네 개의
active at the same time.
데이터 배치가 있다.
And these batches are color-coded.
이 배치는 색상으로 구분된다.
So then we see that GPU 1 runs forward on the blue batch,
그래서 GPU 1은 파란 배치에서 순방향으로 실행하고, 그 다음
then forward on the yellow batch,
노란 배치, 그 다음 초록
then forward on the green batch, then forward on the red batch,
배치, 그 다음 빨간 배치에서 순방향으로 실행하며,
and while GPU 1 is going forward on the yellow batch,
GPU 1이 노란 배치에서 순방향으로 진행하는
we have passed the activations of the blue batch to GPU 1
동안, 우리는 파란 배치의 활성화를 GPU 1 또는
or to GPU 2.
GPU 2로 전달했다.
And GPU 2 can now do forward on the blue batch.
그리고 GPU 2는 이제 파란 배치에서 순방향으로 실행할 수 있다.
So these things can all cascade down and happen in parallel.
이 모든 것들은 연속적으로 진행되고 병렬로 발생할 수 있다.
And then the same pattern repeats
그리고 같은 패턴이 역방향
during the backward pass.
패스 동안 반복된다.
We can interleave these different microbatches
우리는 이 서로 다른 마이크로 배치를 서로 다른 GPU를
as we pipeline them through the different GPUs.
통해 파이프라인으로 처리하면서 교차할 수 있다.
And in this case with four-way pipeline parallelism with four
이 경우 네 방향 파이프라인 병렬 처리와 네 개의
microbatches, the max theoretical MFU
마이크로 배치로, 최대 이론적 MFU는 이
is just the fraction of this graph, which is not white.
그래프의 흰색이 아닌 부분의 비율이다.
And that increases now to 57% which is pretty good.
그리고 그것은 이제 57%로 증가하며, 꽤 좋은 수치이다.
So with pipeline parallelism, in theory,
그래서 파이프라인 병렬 처리로 이론적으로,
if you go to lots and lots of microbatches,
많은 마이크로 배치로 가면 MFU가
then your MFU is going to be good
좋을 것이다. 왜냐하면 많은 작업을
because you can do a lot of work in parallel.
병렬로 수행할 수 있기 때문이다.
But the more microbatches, you have,
하지만 마이크로 배치가 많아질수록,
they need to store all the activations in memory.
모든 활성화를 메모리에 저장해야 한다.
So now you need to do activation checkpointing,
그래서 이제 활성화 체크포인팅을 수행해야 하고, 그러면
and then you think like, oh crap.
'아, 큰일이다.'라고 생각하게 된다.
How do I tune these things?
이것들을 어떻게 조정하지?
Should I have more pipeline parallelism?
더 많은 파이프라인 병렬 처리를 해야 할까?
Should I have fewer microbatches?
마이크로 배치를 줄여야 할까?
Should I have more aggressive activation checkpointing?
더 공격적인 활성화 체크포인팅을 해야 할까?
And then should I also layer data parallelism on top of that?
그리고 그 위에 데이터 병렬 처리를 추가해야 할까?
I don't know.
모르겠다.
What are you going to do?
어떻게 할 건가?
Maximize MFU.
MFU를 극대화하라.
You're going to try to tune all of those knobs
훈련 파이프라인의 MFU를
to maximize the MFU of your training pipeline.
극대화하기 위해 모든 조정을 시도할 것이다.
Then the last one is tensor parallelism.
마지막은 텐서 병렬성입니다.
So this one you're going to split on that model dimension.
이 모델 차원에서 나누게 됩니다.
So basically what we're going to do
기본적으로 모델에
is we have a lot of weight matrices in our model.
많은 가중치 행렬이 있습니다.
All those weight matrices are like computing XW equals
모든 가중치 행렬은 XW가
Y. That's basically what we're doing over and over again inside
Y와 같다는 계산을 합니다. 이것이 우리의 변환기 내부에서 반복적으로
of our transformer.
수행되는 것입니다.
Now the idea is we'll split each weight matrix across GPUs.
이제 각 가중치 행렬을 GPU에 걸쳐 나눌 것입니다.
And now this is different from FSDP
이것은 FSDP와 다릅니다.
because we're actually splitting a single weight
왜냐하면 실제로 단일 가중치 행렬을
matrix across GPUs.
GPU에 걸쳐 나누기 때문입니다.
And now there's no communication.
이제 통신이 없습니다.
Now we do a block matrix multiply.
이제 블록 행렬 곱셈을 수행합니다.
So each GPU is now computing a slice of that matrix multiply
각 GPU는 전체 입력에 대한 행렬 곱셈의 슬라이스를
on the full input.
계산합니다.
So in this case, we split our weight matrix
이 경우, 가중치 행렬을
into W1, W2, W3, W4.
W1, W2, W3, W4로 나눕니다.
And then each GPU just computes a slice of that matrix,
그런 다음 각 GPU는 해당 행렬의 슬라이스를
multiply to compute a slice of the output.
계산하여 출력의 슬라이스를 계산합니다.
And then a problem is that, now after you do that forward pass,
문제는, 이제 순전파를 수행한 후 모든
then you need to gather the activations across all the GPUs
GPU에서 활성화를 모아 다음 순전파를 수행해야
to do the next forward pass.
한다는 것입니다.
There's a slight trick, which is,
약간의 요령이 있습니다.
if you have two of these layers in sequence,
두 개의 이러한 레이어가
you can actually get away with not gathering in between two
연속으로 있을 경우, 두 레이어 사이에 모으지 않고도 진행할 수
layers.
있습니다.
So if you have two layers, you can sit down in a quiet place
두 개의 레이어가 있다면, 조용한 곳에 앉아 이 작업을
and work through this.
진행할 수 있습니다.
You split the first weight matrix
첫 번째 가중치 행렬을 열
into column-shaped chunks.
모양의 청크로 나눕니다.
Then you split the second weight matrix into row-shaped chunks.
그런 다음 두 번째 가중치 행렬을 행 모양의 청크로 나눕니다.
And if you do all this, then it all
이 모든 것을 수행하면 블록 행렬
works out magically because of the magic and mystery
곱셈의 마법과 신비 덕분에 모든 것이
of block matrix multiplication.
마법처럼 작동합니다.
And you see that the final output
최종 출력을
you can compute as an inner product like structure
Y와 U의 블록 행렬 곱셈의 내적
of these block matrix multiplies of Y and U.
구조로 계산할 수 있습니다.
So then you basically can have two layers of matrix multiply
따라서 기본적으로 여러 GPU에 걸쳐 나누어진 두 개의 행렬 곱셈
that are split across multiple GPUs.
레이어를 가질 수 있습니다.
And then they only need to communicate
그리고 그들은 매 두 레이어의
at the end of every two layers.
끝에서만 통신해야 합니다.
And this actually works out nicely
이것은 변환기가 FFN에서
because remember transformers have a two layer MLP in the FFN.
두 개의 레이어 MLP를 가지고 있다는 것을 기억하면 잘 작동합니다.
So this is a really nice trick that
그래서 이것은 변환기가 항상 가지고
plays really nicely into the two layer MLPs
있는 두 개의 레이어 MLP에 잘
that transformers always have.
맞는 정말 좋은 요령입니다.
So it's pretty common in big transformers
그래서 큰 변환기에서
to use tensor parallelism, this like two layer tensor
텐서 병렬성을 사용하는 것은 꽤 일반적이며,
parallelism trick on the MLP in a transformer.
변환기의 MLP에서 이 두 레이어 텐서 병렬성 요령을 사용합니다.
So that's basically all of our mechanisms for splitting up
이것이 GPU에 걸쳐 계산을 나누기
computation across GPUs.
위한 모든 메커니즘입니다.
Which one is the best?
어떤 것이 가장 좋습니까?
The actual answer is all of them.
실제 답은 모두입니다.
So in practice, we're going to use ND parallelism.
실제로 우리는 ND 병렬성을 사용할 것입니다.
We saw already an example of two-dimensional parallelism
이미 HSRP로 2차원 병렬성의 예를
with HSRP.
보았습니다.
In practice, the current state of the art
실제로 현재 최첨단은 4차원
is like four dimensional parallelism.
병렬성과 같습니다.
If we go back to Lama, we see that they are training with
Lama로 돌아가면, 그들은 16,000개의 GPU로
on their biggest training run with 16,000 GPUs.
가장 큰 훈련을 하고 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
They're using 8 way tensor parallelism, 16 way context
그들은 8방향 텐서 병렬성, 16방향 컨텍스트
parallelism, 16 way pipeline parallelism, and 8 data way
병렬성, 16방향 파이프라인 병렬성, 8방향 데이터
parallelism all at the same time.
병렬성을 동시에 사용하고 있습니다.
And if you're careful, different mechanisms of parallelism
그리고 조심하면, 서로 다른 병렬 처리 메커니즘은 서로 다른 통신
have different communication requirements.
요구 사항을 가지고 있습니다.
So if you're careful in how you arrange these different axes
그래서 클러스터의 서로 다른 병렬 처리
of parallelism along your cluster,
축을 어떻게 배열하는지
you can try to take advantage of that varying
조심하면, 전체
speeds of communication across your whole cluster.
클러스터에서 통신 속도의 변화를 활용할 수 있습니다.
That's basically a whirlwind tour
이것이 대규모 분산 훈련에
of large-scale distributed training.
대한 간단한 개요입니다.
So the takeaway for today is that an individual GPU
오늘의 핵심은 개별 GPU가 기본적으로
is basically a generalizable parallel computing machine.
일반화 가능한 병렬 컴퓨팅 머신이라는 것입니다.
A GPU cluster is a giant massively parallel machine
GPU 클러스터는 수만 개, 어쩌면 수십만 개의 개별 GPU로
with tens of thousands, maybe hundreds of thousands
구성된 거대한 대규모 병렬 머신이며,
of individual GPUs, and we want to program as one big unit.
우리는 이를 하나의 큰 단위로 프로그래밍하고자 합니다.
And then we talked about multiple different mechanisms
그리고 우리는 큰 클러스터에서 계산을
of parallelizing our computation across big clusters,
병렬화하는 여러 가지 메커니즘과 메모리를 절약하기
as well as one trick activation checkpointing for saving memory,
위한 트릭인 활성화 체크포인팅, 그리고 이러한
and then the one guiding light metric that you're always
파이프라인을 설계할 때 항상 최적화하려고 하는
trying to optimize when you design these pipelines, which
유일한 지표인 모델 플롭스 활용도에
is model flops utilization.
대해 이야기했습니다.
So the next time you're going out and training
다음에 수만 개의 GPU로
on tens of thousands of GPUs, hope you keep this in mind.
훈련할 때 이 점을 기억하시길 바랍니다.
And let me know so I can borrow your tens of thousands of GPUs.
그리고 제가 당신의 수만 개의 GPU를 빌릴 수 있도록 알려주세요.